<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>http://deshipu.art/</id>
  <title>deshipu.art - Posted in 2017</title>
  <updated>2024-08-07T20:33:03.375104+00:00</updated>
  <link href="http://deshipu.art/"/>
  <link href="http://deshipu.art/blog/2017/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://ablog.readthedocs.org/" version="0.10.33">ABlog</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-27579/log-71833/</id>
    <title>Fixed Second Version</title>
    <updated>2017-12-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="fixed-second-version"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2017-12-21 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../projects/project-27579/#project-27579"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Blinka&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also fixed the short on the second version of the board, and
uploaded the design to OSHPark here:  &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://oshpark.com/shared_projects/xMggaR8L"&gt;https://oshpark.com/shared_projects/xMggaR8L&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-27579/log-71833/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2017-12-21 in project-27579.</summary>
    <published>2017-12-21T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-27579/log-71853/</id>
    <title>Third Version</title>
    <updated>2017-12-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="third-version"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2017-12-22 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../projects/project-27579/#project-27579"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Blinka&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I finally got my hands on a vector version of the Blinka logo, and I
immediately started working on the third version of the board. Of
course the file was a horrible mess of spurious nodes, but after a
couple of hours of cleaning it up, and some simple operations on the
shapes, I have the basic layers ready:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-27579/images/5498281513945166377.png" src="projects/project-27579/images/5498281513945166377.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time the board outline is much simplified, to avoid problems with
cutting it out. I realized that there is a fifth color that I didn’t
use — the raw FR4 board — so I used it here. I also made it much
bigger this time — so that it fits in the 5×5cm square. That should
give me enough space to fit the SAMD21, the coin cell battery, the
power switch, and as many pads as I can route conveniently on a single
side. I’m also considering just slapping a Trinket M0 on it — we will
see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-27579/log-71853/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2017-12-22 in project-27579.</summary>
    <published>2017-12-22T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-27629/log-71971/</id>
    <title>Testing at the Fab</title>
    <updated>2017-12-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="testing-at-the-fab"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2017-12-26 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../projects/project-27629/#project-27629"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;µGame&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently some fab houses can do firmware programming and testing of
the devices right in the factory — you just have to provide detailed
step-by-step instructions on how to do it. So I started work on the
firmware flashing guide and on the test program. I also modified the
version 8 PCB design that I have on order from Aisler to add the VCC
pad to the bottom of the board — together with SWDCLK, SWDIO and GND
they form the programming interface. The STLink clone I had didn’t
require VCC connected, but it also didn’t program the chips
consistently. The J-Link is consistent, but requires VCC to drive its
own programming pins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m also working on the guide itself, and one of the things I will
need is a drawing of the board with the pads marked. So I made this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-27629/images/4955251514252282765.png" src="projects/project-27629/images/4955251514252282765.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still need to write the actual test program, and see if I can
somehow put the CircuitPython and the bootloader into a single binary
to be flashed — that would simplify and speed up the process.
Unfortunately the test program will still need to be copied over USB —
because I also want this and the flash chip tested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-27629/log-71971/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2017-12-26 in project-27629.</summary>
    <published>2017-12-26T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-27629/log-72065/</id>
    <title>nGame is µGame, only Smaller</title>
    <updated>2017-12-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="ngame-is-game-only-smaller"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2017-12-28 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../projects/project-27629/#project-27629"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;µGame&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I was designing the &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../projects/project-19371/#project-19371"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;D1 Mini X-Pad Shield&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; , the &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../projects/project-21578/#project-21578"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;PewPew FeatherWing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and most recently µGame, I struggled with the same problem: how to fit
the direction pads and fire buttons on as small PCB area as possible,
while still keeping them usable. I think I have tested pretty much any
type of SMD buttons on offer from China, tried different layouts and
packing schemes, and even did some uncanny experiments with fitting
larger buttons to smaller footprints. But I never quite had the
courage to really push the limits. Until now, that is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-27629/images/388361514475842212.jpg" src="projects/project-27629/images/388361514475842212.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what happens to µGame when you leave it in your pants pocket
in the dryer and let it shrink. It uses the same ST7725S display that
I used in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../projects/project-27033/#project-27033"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Trinket M0 TFT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; — even the driver fits, you just have to adjust the screen size in it.
It uses the smallest 2-pad buttons I could find — they use 1206
resistor footprints. The SAMD21 microcontroller has no additional
flash storage this time, so we are very constrained in what fits there
— none of the demos for µGame I had worked out of the box, that’s why
the photo shows just random pixels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;———- more ———-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-27629/images/2744301514476082949.jpg" src="projects/project-27629/images/2744301514476082949.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the back you can see the 2032 coin cell battery, the power switch
and the voltage regulator circuit, the USB socket and the shottky
diode that isolates the battery from the USB power. There is no
battery charging, no audio output, no battery monitoring and even no
reset button (you can reset it to get to the bootloader by shorting
one of the vias to ground). I still have some free space in that
corner (and it’s also free on the other side), so I might add a hole
for a keychain there…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I said, the memory constraints are severe, and I haven’t written a
game or demo that actually runs on it, but I’m sure I can do it. In
the worst case, I can drop the wasteful CircuitPython and program this
thing with Arduino.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This whole thing is basically just to see how hard it would be to
build (moderately), and use (hard, you have to press the buttons with
your fingernails). Also, because I kinda felt bad switching the final
µGame version to use old Nokia phone batteries after submitting this
to the coin cell contest. So here, a version that still runs on the
coin cell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also big thanks to the hackers on the &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-5373&lt;/span&gt; for helping me debug the power/USB problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-27629/log-72065/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2017-12-28 in project-27629.</summary>
    <published>2017-12-28T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-27629/log-72107/</id>
    <title>Final Prototype</title>
    <updated>2017-12-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="final-prototype"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2017-12-29 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../projects/project-27629/#project-27629"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;µGame&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The version 8 PCBs arrived from Aisler, together with the stencil, and
it looks great this time!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-27629/images/1334281514587551825.jpg" src="projects/project-27629/images/1334281514587551825.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please especially note the smooth edges of the board, without any
trace of the panelization tabs. Of course I immediately assembled one
of the boards and tested it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-27629/images/4611061514587644013.jpg" src="projects/project-27629/images/4611061514587644013.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It works great. Please note the much nicer alignment of the chips, and
the fact that there are no parts under your fingers. One of the
buttons had to be moved a little to the side, but it’s actually better
that way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course there were still changes needed, but they are so small, that
I can confidently send the gerber files to the fab without ordering
one more test board. The changes included adding one more debug pad
for connecting VCC, adding holes to the debug pads so that it’s easier
to connect probes to them, moving some of the resistors a little to
make them easier to solder, and fixing the stencil to include the pads
for the USB port, and exclude the holes of the power switch
(workarounds for Fritzing’s weirdness).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also wrote the step-by-step testing instructions, and made a test
program:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-27629/images/1940471514587965047.jpg" src="projects/project-27629/images/1940471514587965047.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So everything is ready for fabrication. I will now send all that to
the fab house, and see what they think about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-27629/log-72107/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2017-12-29 in project-27629.</summary>
    <published>2017-12-29T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>
