<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>http://deshipu.art/</id>
  <title>deshipu.art - Posts in project-18120</title>
  <updated>2024-08-07T20:45:04.555582+00:00</updated>
  <link href="http://deshipu.art/"/>
  <link href="http://deshipu.art/blog/category/project-18120/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://ablog.readthedocs.org/" version="0.10.33">ABlog</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-18120/log-55787/</id>
    <title>Different Chips</title>
    <updated>2017-03-28T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="different-chips"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2017-03-28 in &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-18120&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While ordering the different colors for the mini 8x8 LED matrices, I
couldn’t help but notice the bi-color and RGB matrices in the same
size. The RGB one would be a bit difficult to route for me on a two-
sided PCB, but I decided to give the bi-color one a try and ordered
it. It should be super-easy to route, because the row pins are
actually in order on both sides, and in the middle are the common
column pins. The only problem is that I would need to use the 28-pin
HT16K33 chip, and it would need to sit across the middle column – but
with good flat wire cutters that seemed doable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently the matrices arrived, and also the PCB from OSHPark that I
ordered to test the bi-color matrix:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-18120/images/9935751490652126686.png" src="projects/project-18120/images/9935751490652126686.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see, I didn’t care about the order of rows and columns, and
just routed them in random order – assuming I can fix that in
software later on. Unfortunately, the matrix didn’t work. A closer
inspection revealed that I got the common-anode matrix, whereas the
HT16K33 can only handle the common cathode ones. Bummer. I ordered the
correct, common-cathode matrices then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But now I have a bunch of matrices I can’t drive easily, and this
feeling that I should really do something with them. I looked for a
chip that could handle them, but in vain. &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://hackaday.io/page/2976-alternative-to-ht16k33-for-a-common-anode-bi-color-matrix"&gt;I posted a question to the stack&lt;/a&gt; , and updated it with what I found. And then, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://hackaday.iohttps://hackaday.io/hacker/157453"&gt;&amp;#64;Jeremy Gilbert&lt;/a&gt;  suggested a family of chips that I forgot about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You see, there are those charlieplexed LED FeatherWings that Adafruit
has, with a very cool IS31FL3731 chip. &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/adafruit/micropython-adafruit-is31fl3731"&gt;I even wrote a MicroPython library for driving them once!&lt;/a&gt;  But I didn’t realize that &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.issi.com/US/product-analog-fxled-driver.shtml"&gt;there is a whole family of those chips&lt;/a&gt; , and they are not only for charlieplexed displays, also for regular
matrices. And they are much more modern than the venerable HT16K33,
and have cool features, like the ability to set the brightness of
every pixel individually, built-in blinking and animations, and even
changing the brightness according to audio input!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I decided to try and also make a couple of shields with those. We
will see how well that works, for a start I ordered a board for the
simplest IS31FL3728 chip:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-18120/images/4379281490652774440.png" src="projects/project-18120/images/4379281490652774440.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It will probably be a bit tricky to solder, being in a QFN package,
but nothing that I didn’t manage before. I will keep you updated.\&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-18120/log-55787/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2017-03-28 in project-18120.</summary>
    <published>2017-03-28T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-18120/log-56595/</id>
    <title>Deluxe Matrix</title>
    <updated>2017-04-05T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="deluxe-matrix"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2017-04-05 in &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-18120&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I now created a new project for trying out the new chips: &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-20941&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-18120/log-56595/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2017-04-05 in project-18120.</summary>
    <published>2017-04-05T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-18120/log-56671/</id>
    <title>The Curse Strikes Again</title>
    <updated>2017-04-06T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="the-curse-strikes-again"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2017-04-06 in &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-18120&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember when I wrote that I ran out of mistakes to make in this
project? Was I ever wrong. The PCBs just came from DirtyPCBs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-18120/images/7627611491468851286.jpg" src="projects/project-18120/images/7627611491468851286.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s not the kind of panelization that I expected… Of course I
immediately downloaded back the zip file with gerbers and checked it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-18120/images/7366911491468975662.png" src="projects/project-18120/images/7366911491468975662.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yup, that’s what I sent them to make (unless they do some processing
to it). Of course I didn’t notice a problem, because the preview at
DirtyPCBs is broken since they switched to the new website, and
doesn’t show the board outline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I have a few days of dremeling before me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-18120/log-56671/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2017-04-06 in project-18120.</summary>
    <published>2017-04-06T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-18120/log-56761/</id>
    <title>Some Good News</title>
    <updated>2017-04-07T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="some-good-news"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2017-04-07 in &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-18120&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite all the problems, I’m persevering. Today the common-cathode
bi-color matrices arrived, and I was able to try them with the
HT16K33:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-18120/images/7119231491553580125.jpg" src="projects/project-18120/images/7119231491553580125.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, the pattern is pretty much random, because I still need to
adjust the software for the pretty much random column and row
assignment I made. But you can see the colors, and they are nice (the
slight variations of color on the photo are due to the camera sensor
interfering with the PWM).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-18120/log-56761/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2017-04-07 in project-18120.</summary>
    <published>2017-04-07T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-18120/log-60306/</id>
    <title>Competition</title>
    <updated>2017-05-28T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="competition"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2017-05-28 in &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-18120&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As they say, be careful what you are wishing for, you might get it. My
main motivation for making all those D1 Mini shields and selling them
is to make this functionality available – first from my &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://hackaday.iohttps://hackaday.io/hacker/130335"&gt;&amp;#64;Tindie&lt;/a&gt;  shop, and then, hopefully, from Aliexpress and eBay, as it gets
cloned and manufactured cheaply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently WeMos, the very company that makes the D1 Mini boards, has
introduced a new product – a 8x8 LED matrix shield similar to what I
have been making here. Here’s a link: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.aliexpress.com/store/product/Matrix-LED-Shield-V1-0-0-for-WEMOS-D1-mini/1331105_32812932291.html"&gt;https://www.aliexpress.com/store/product/Matrix-LED-Shield-V1-0-0-for-
WEMOS-D1-mini/1331105_32812932291.html&lt;/a&gt;  – thanks to &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://hackaday.iohttps://hackaday.io/hacker/3459"&gt;&amp;#64;davedarko&lt;/a&gt;  for the tip!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, this is not a clone of my shields. It’s a complete re-make of
the idea, with a different chip on board, using different pins and
protocol for communication, and not software compatible. As far as I
can tell there are not libraries or code examples for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ordered one out of curiosity and will experiment with it, but for
now let’s see what I we can infer from the photos. The chip used is
AIP1640, which seems to be a cheap clone of the TM1640 LED driver,
produced by &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://titanmec.com/"&gt;http://titanmec.com/&lt;/a&gt; . There seem to be no English datasheets for it, but there is one in
Chinese available from &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://titanmec.com/index.php/product/view/id/305/typeid/59.html"&gt;http://titanmec.com/index.php/product/view/id/305/typeid/59.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This chip can drive up to 8x16 LEDs, so only half the outputs are used
for driving the 8x8 matrix – you could drive a double or bi-color
matrix with it (like this one: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.aliexpress.com/item/8x8-LED-Red-Green-Dual-Color-Dot-Matrix-Display-Module-TM1640-for-Arduino/32476051733.html"&gt;https://www.aliexpress.com/item/8x8-LED-Red-Green-Dual-Color-Dot-
Matrix-Display-Module-TM1640-for-Arduino/32476051733.html&lt;/a&gt; ). The inputs are connected to D1 Mini’s MOSI and SCK pins through
transistors, because it’s a 5V device. The protocol it uses for
communication is a weird mix of SPI and I²C: you send serial data, but
because there is no chip-select pin, you denote start of transmission
with I2Ć-like start condition. There are no addresses, though – the
device basically owns the pins it is connected to all the time. The
driver does support PWM, but you can only change the brightness of the
whole matrix, and not individual pixels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There seems to be an Arduino library for the TM1638, that also
supports TM1640, but it seems to be only for 7-segment displays. The
library can be found here: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/rjbatista/tm1638-library"&gt;https://github.com/rjbatista/tm1638-library&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of the TM1638, I can’t understand why they didn’t use that
chip, or one of the other LED driver chips manufactured by Titanmec
(they have quite an interesting offer, see &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://titanmec.com/index.php/product/lists/typeid/59.html"&gt;http://titanmec.com/index.php/product/lists/typeid/59.html&lt;/a&gt; ). For instance the TM1629 or TM1638 ( &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://titanmec.com/index.php/product/view/id/303/typeid/59.html"&gt;http://titanmec.com/index.php/product/view/id/303/typeid/59.html&lt;/a&gt; , English datasheet at &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://retrocip.cz/files/tm1638.pdf"&gt;https://retrocip.cz/files/tm1638.pdf&lt;/a&gt; ) – it’s smaller, supports 8x8 LEDs and uses a proper SPI protocol
that plays nice with other devices. Or use the venerable HT16K33,
which is well tested, has proper I2C and already has a lot of existing
libraries. I suspect they got a really good deal on those clones…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perosnally, I find the TM1680 particularly interesting, as it should
be capable of driving an RGB matrix with I2C: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://titanmec.com/index.php/product/view/id/393.html"&gt;http://titanmec.com/index.php/product/view/id/393.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the mean time, I will keep selling my own matrix shields on Tindie
– they can’t compete with these price-wise, but I think they are much
easier to use, at least for now.\&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-18120/log-60306/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2017-05-28 in project-18120.</summary>
    <published>2017-05-28T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>
