<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>http://deshipu.art/</id>
  <title>deshipu.art - Posts in project-7522</title>
  <updated>2024-08-07T20:31:59.058944+00:00</updated>
  <link href="http://deshipu.art/"/>
  <link href="http://deshipu.art/blog/category/project-7522/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://ablog.readthedocs.org/" version="0.10.33">ABlog</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-7522/log-24510/</id>
    <title>Acrylic Nuts and Bolts</title>
    <updated>2015-09-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="acrylic-nuts-and-bolts"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2015-09-01 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-7522/#project-7522"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Hacking the MeArm&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the more important challenges in the design of MeArm is making
it as light as possible, especially at the end of the arm, where there
is the longest lever and the inertia is the worst. But if you look at
the robot, it has 10 metal bolts in there, which are quite heavy. So
what can be done without laser-cutting my own version of the gripper
that would use fewer bolts?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was looking for bolts for the &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-6608/#project-6608"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Talk Ranking Machine&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; , I stumbled upon those acrylic bolts. They are like completely normal
nuts and bolts, except they are made out of acrylic, instead of metal.
And they are light. Sure, they are not as strong as metal bolts, but
they are as strong as the rest of MeArm, so it doesn’t matter. They
fit this project perfectly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-7522/images/965201441142440985.jpg" src="projects/project-7522/images/965201441142440985.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, there is a trick to using them. You will need one normal metal
bolt, to thread the holes first. Preferably several times, and make
sure you get all the way through, because if you don’t, you are going
to break the acrylic bolts trying to force them in. After screwing the
bolt in and out several times, you can screw in the acrylic bolt, and
cut it to size with wire clippers. Easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see on the picture that I didn’t replace one bolt inside the
robot, and the four bolts in the base. The bolts in the base are
longer than the acrylic bolts I had, and they don’t matter for the
weight of the arm itself anyways, and the bolt in the middle was just
too hard to get to without disassembling the whole robot first, so I
let it be. It’s close to the center of gravity anyways, so it
shouldn’t matter that much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-7522/log-24510/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2015-09-01 in project-7522.</summary>
    <published>2015-09-01T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-7522/log-47571/</id>
    <title>Still Alive</title>
    <updated>2016-10-12T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="still-alive"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2016-10-12 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-7522/#project-7522"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Hacking the MeArm&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I dug out this project. I never actually intended to abandon it for
so long, but somehow that’s exactly what happened. Today I started
preparing for the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://pl.pycon.org"&gt;PyCon.PL&lt;/a&gt;  confernece, and looked at the shelf, and there it was. We are going
to do some Micro:Bit hacking at the conference, and I thought: “Hey,
it’s a good thing to connect a Micro:Bit to!” So I took it out, blew
the dust from it, replaced two broken bolts (those acrylic bolts are
delicate when you tighten them too much) and added a bunch of wires to
the servos:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-7522/images/2902801476262046533.jpg" src="projects/project-7522/images/2902801476262046533.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every servo has now two extra wires: one going to the center tap of
the pot, and one going to the motor. Why? Because I want to be able to
do position and force sensing! Probably not right now and not with the
Micro:Bit, but I really want to do some experiments with complain
motion and such.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-7522/log-47571/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2016-10-12 in project-7522.</summary>
    <published>2016-10-12T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>
