<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>http://deshipu.art/</id>
  <title>deshipu.art - Posts in project-182310</title>
  <updated>2024-08-07T20:35:29.477866+00:00</updated>
  <link href="http://deshipu.art/"/>
  <link href="http://deshipu.art/blog/category/project-182310/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://ablog.readthedocs.org/" version="0.10.33">ABlog</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-182310/log-199384/</id>
    <title>PCB Design</title>
    <updated>2021-10-24T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="pcb-design"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2021-10-24 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-182310/#project-182310"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;NHYTGB Keyboard&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m going to start with just a very simple mechanical design, just a
PCB with the switches on both sides. I can think about improvements if
the basic idea proves workable. So after compiling the very latest
version of Fritzing (the appimage they released doesn’t work on my
system), I went to work and created this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-182310/images/9909721635033665885.png" src="projects/project-182310/images/9909721635033665885.png" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-182310/images/4102431635033678382.png" src="projects/project-182310/images/4102431635033678382.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, the traces have right angle bends. I don’t care. This is a
prototype. I can clean it up some other time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also added a joystick and a d-pad on the front side, for those
moments when you are not typing. The USB socket is on the bottom,
because that’s where many devices have their socket as well — you can
use a short OTG cable to connect them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-182310/log-199384/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2021-10-24 in project-182310.</summary>
    <published>2021-10-24T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-182310/log-199929/</id>
    <title>Version One</title>
    <updated>2021-11-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="version-one"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2021-11-02 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-182310/#project-182310"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;NHYTGB Keyboard&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I assembled the first version of the device, and tested it
mechanically (I still need to write the code for it). As far as I can
tell so far, mechanically it should work, though the thumb keys are
pretty awkward, and the whole thing is really sensitive to the size of
one’s palms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-182310/images/72101635878751504.jpg" src="projects/project-182310/images/72101635878751504.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-182310/images/6332761635878768772.jpg" src="projects/project-182310/images/6332761635878768772.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-182310/log-199929/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2021-11-02 in project-182310.</summary>
    <published>2021-11-02T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-182310/log-200107/</id>
    <title>Bodge, Bodge, Bodge</title>
    <updated>2021-11-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="bodge-bodge-bodge"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2021-11-06 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-182310/#project-182310"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;NHYTGB Keyboard&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally the weekend is here, and I had some time to actually program
and test this device. Right away I found this tiny little problem on
the PCB:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-182310/images/5371421636231236144.png" src="projects/project-182310/images/5371421636231236144.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to see, but there is a trace between PA01 and PA02 pins. One
is part of the key matrix, the other goes to the analog joystick, so
this would give us some really interesting effects — fortunately I
noticed it, so I could desolder the chip with hot air, cut that trace,
and solder it back again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, I had some fun getting the D-pad and the mouse buttons to work.
For some reason they were ignored. After about an hour of
experimenting, replacing switches, replacing diodes, cutting traces,
adding bodges and so on, I finally figured out what is happening. I
made two footprints for buttons in there, both SMD and THT, so that I
can experiment with different buttons. But I didn’t notice, that the
THT buttons I used this time, have some of the contacts sticking out
on the sides. Those were making contact with the SMD pads, resulting
in the switch always being on. Since the keypad module is event-based,
and the switch was on even before the code started, so we never got a
keypress event, and obviously it also never was released to generated
a key release event, so the key was basically being ignored. To make
it more interesting, those contacts are only one one side, so the
problem was only present for about half of the buttons — depending how
they were rotated. In the end, I just rotated the misbehaving buttons
180° to fix this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-182310/log-200107/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2021-11-06 in project-182310.</summary>
    <published>2021-11-06T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-182310/log-230631/</id>
    <title>Results</title>
    <updated>2024-06-20T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="results"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2024-06-20 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-182310/#project-182310"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;NHYTGB Keyboard&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just realized that I never updated this project with the results of
my experiment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, I’m disappointed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was hoping the muscle memory and learning from a traditional split
keyboard would transfer to this layout, but it turns out that our
muscle memory seems to operate in terms of absolute positions, not
relative movements, and that rotating the keyboard by 90° and flipping
it completely defeats any learning you might have benefited from from
use of a regular keyboard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The keyboard is possible to use, but you basically have to learn to
type on it from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-182310/log-230631/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2024-06-20 in project-182310.</summary>
    <published>2024-06-20T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>
