<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>http://deshipu.art/</id>
  <title>deshipu.art - Posts in project-21578</title>
  <updated>2024-08-07T20:45:05.073489+00:00</updated>
  <link href="http://deshipu.art/"/>
  <link href="http://deshipu.art/blog/category/project-21578/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://ablog.readthedocs.org/" version="0.10.33">ABlog</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-21578/log-145952/</id>
    <title>PewPew Lite Version 4.2</title>
    <updated>2018-05-08T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="pewpew-lite-version-4-2"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2018-05-08 in &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-21578&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had that version designed for quite a while, actually, and even the
PCBs arrived and were lying there in a drawer — but I didn’t have time
to work on them, busy with other projects. Now I moved, and found the
PCBs in a box (and &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://hackaday.io/hacker/7"&gt;&amp;#64;Benchoff &lt;/a&gt; mentioned PewPew in an article), and decided to assemble them and put
up on sale on Tindie. So now there is a new version of the PewPew Lite
on Tinide. For now I only made ten, because that’s how many boards I
had, but I already ordered some more, and more parts, so I will keep
them coming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-21578/images/6945441525792828467.jpg" src="projects/project-21578/images/6945441525792828467.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new version comes with the matrix display already soldered, and
with staggered holes for the pin headers — so that you can simply
friction-fit them without soldering. The connection seems to be good
enough, but if you experience problems, you can always solder them.
There is still no socket for the battery — you will have to solder the
leads directly if you add it. There is simply no room for it on this
board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, you no longer can choose a color. They are all red. It was the
preferred color anyways, yellow ones only got sold when the red ones
ran out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-21578/log-145952/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2018-05-08 in project-21578.</summary>
    <published>2018-05-08T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-21578/log-149325/</id>
    <title>Making it Cheaper Again</title>
    <updated>2018-07-14T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="making-it-cheaper-again"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2018-07-14 in &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-21578&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PewPew Lite FeatherWing is one of my favorite designs, and I think
it’s really great for learning programming games — actually better
than the &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-27629&lt;/span&gt; , because it’s so much simpler. The shield itself is pretty cheap,
too. Unfortunately, you still need to have a Feather M0 (or, even
better, M0 Express) to use it, and that’s actually twice as expensive
as the shield itself. Add the LiPo battery to the mix, and you could
instead buy an ODROID GO or something similar. This is problematic
especially if you want to organize a workshop — you either make a
workshop for the rich, or find a sponsor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have already tried to lower the price of the whole thing by putting
the microcontroller directly on the device — basically copying the
Trinket M0 schematic for that — but the resulting device was pretty
complex to make, and I was never quite happy with it. Plus, you still
needed the LiPo battery and its charging circuit and all that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I sat down and redesigned the latest version of PewPew
completely, using the knowledge I gained from µGame and from the &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-100853&lt;/span&gt; to simplify it as much as possible, while still keeping its basic
functionality. That’s how I came up with PewPew 6.0:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-21578/images/9513911531579693448.png" src="projects/project-21578/images/9513911531579693448.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s exactly the size of two AA batteries, because that’s what it is
going to be using for power. It uses the good old HT16K33 chip, just
like the PewPew Lite, which simplifies things a lot. However, the
buttons are handled directly by the microcontroller now, because to
have them handled by the HT16K33, I would need six extra resistors,
and I tried to minimize the parts count. To get rid of Shottky diodes
or transistors for isolating the USB VBUS, I simply used the power
switch to switch between the battery power and the USB power. I might
even skip the voltage regulator and make it always run on battery
power. Apart from that, there are the six buttons, the bi-color
matrix, the SAMD21 microcontroller itself, two pull-up resistors for
the I2C bus and two filter capacitors — that’s it. Everything is
routed on the top layer of the PCB (the bottom is one big ground
plane), and all parts (except for the battery holder) are mounted on
top, to simplify assembly. I’m using the QFN version of SAMD21,
because it’s slightly cheaper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I considered using other chips than the HT16K33 for driving the
matrix, in particular, simple shift registers to do all the work in
the microcontroller, but in the end the HT16K33 is cheap enough and
does all the work for me. In the future, I might consider switching to
charlieplexed SMD bi-color LEDs and driving them from the MCU pins
directly — that would probably shave a few dollars from the BOM at the
cost of more work with assembling it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-21578/log-149325/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2018-07-14 in project-21578.</summary>
    <published>2018-07-14T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-21578/log-155174/</id>
    <title>Replaced by PewPew Standalone</title>
    <updated>2018-10-23T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="replaced-by-pewpew-standalone"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2018-10-23 in &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-21578&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this still works and is fully compatible with all other PewPew
boards, and while I still sell it on Tindie, check out the new devices
over at &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-159733&lt;/span&gt; — they are bigger and cheaper, though no color display.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-21578/log-155174/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2018-10-23 in project-21578.</summary>
    <published>2018-10-23T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-21578/log-165753/</id>
    <title>D1 Mini Shield</title>
    <updated>2019-07-15T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="d1-mini-shield"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2019-07-15 in &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-21578&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been mostly working on the &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-159733&lt;/span&gt; recently, but some people still prefer the PewPew Lite version, mostly
for its color display and ability to work with the ESP8266 Feather. So
after I finally found reasonably tiny buttons for &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-165983&lt;/span&gt; , I decided to also make a version of the PewPew Lite in form of a D1
Mini shield. As an additional challenge I wanted to make it
electrically identical to the FeatherWing. After two nights, I had the
design:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-21578/images/3869751563223148383.png" src="projects/project-21578/images/3869751563223148383.png" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-21578/images/4679431563223184652.png" src="projects/project-21578/images/4679431563223184652.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not perfect. Ideally, all the resistors would be under the LED
matrix, but there simply wasn’t enough room to fit all the traces
there. But I managed to do it, even if it required a thousand vias. &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://oshpark.com/shared_projects/i3DM7Qay"&gt;I ordered the PCB from OSHPark&lt;/a&gt; , and promptly forgot about the whole thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today the boards came, so I assembled one. I found a bi-color matrix
in my drawer, but I only found 3 of the buttons — I’m still waiting
for the package with more of them. So I only soldered what I had, to
test how the menu works:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-21578/images/2511091563223374398.JPG" src="projects/project-21578/images/2511091563223374398.JPG" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since CircuitPython no longer supports ESP8266, I had to port the Pew
library to MicroPython — that was easy enough, with just changing all
the timing functions to use utime, and all i2c calls to use the
machine module. After I did that, I wanted to upload the code to
GitHub, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/pewpew-game/pew-pewpewlite-4.x-micropython"&gt;but discovered that it’s already there&lt;/a&gt;  — I have ported it once already and forgot about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the missing button arrive I will finish this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-21578/log-165753/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2019-07-15 in project-21578.</summary>
    <published>2019-07-15T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-21578/log-165851/</id>
    <title>Buttons</title>
    <updated>2019-07-18T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="buttons"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2019-07-18 in &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-21578&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The buttons came today, so I finished it. It’s not the prettiest
soldering job, and the buttons are not quite aligned, but it works and
I can move on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-21578/images/2270791563434837459.JPG" src="projects/project-21578/images/2270791563434837459.JPG" /&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-21578/log-165851/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2019-07-18 in project-21578.</summary>
    <published>2019-07-18T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>
