<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>http://deshipu.art/</id>
  <title>deshipu.art - Posts in project-174917</title>
  <updated>2024-08-07T20:34:12.944742+00:00</updated>
  <link href="http://deshipu.art/"/>
  <link href="http://deshipu.art/blog/category/project-174917/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://ablog.readthedocs.org/" version="0.10.33">ABlog</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-174917/log-183828/</id>
    <title>Fork</title>
    <updated>2020-09-20T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="fork"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2020-09-20 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-174917/#project-174917"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Dorsch 48k Keyboard&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m splitting this project from &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-174095/#project-174095"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Dorsch 40k Keyboard&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; , because it has acquired life of its own, the keyboard being my main
daily keyboard now. I’m still doing some cosmetic tweaks and changes
to the layout and code, but it is mostly as I want it to be, and it’s
way more comfortable than traditional keyboards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So just to catch up from the previous project: I made this minimal,
40-key keyboard with low-profile chocolate switches just to see if
such a small keyboard layout could even work. It turned out that it
not only works, but makes it much easier to learn touch typing for me,
so I started using it as my default keyboard. After a few days I
identified a few annoyances, some of which I was able to fix with
layout tweaks, but some required extra keys to be present. So I
designed a bigger version with a popular “planck” layout. And that’s
where we are now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-174917/log-183828/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2020-09-20 in project-174917.</summary>
    <published>2020-09-20T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-174917/log-183829/</id>
    <title>Undoing 150 Years of Bad Design</title>
    <updated>2020-09-20T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="undoing-150-years-of-bad-design"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2020-09-20 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-174917/#project-174917"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Dorsch 48k Keyboard&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Computer keyboards are sub-optimal. Everybody knows that. You can find
hundreds of articles extolling the virtues of alternate layouts that
tell the story of how first typewriters had their keys in an
alphabetic order, but they would jam, so they have been rearranged to
slow the typist down and avoid jamming. Those stories are mostly made
up, and virtually all research that shows substantial improvements
from using layouts like Dvorak is done by the proponents of those
layouts themselves. People get so focused on that debate, that they
ignore other problems computer keyboards have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typewriters were complex, precise mechanical devices, very expensive
to make. That means that if there was a change to the design that made
it slightly less comfortable or required getting used to, but made the
machine easier to build, it was embraced. Today there is no reason to
keep following all those design decisions, but they have become
tradition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take the staggering of the keys. If you look at a traditional
keyboard, you will note that the Q key is shifted by ¼ horizontally
from A, and that A is similarly shifted by ½ from Z. The reason for
this is not human convenience, it’s because the keys were originally
mounted on metal stems, and there needed to be room for the stems to
go all the way up to the rest of the mechanism. This doesn’t seem to
matter much, until you start to learn proper touch-typing and they
tell you that your fingers should follow the “columns” of keys. What
columns, you ask, they are all jumbled up! Well, the columns that
would be there if they weren’t jumbled up:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-174917/images/7376041600594218507.png" src="projects/project-174917/images/7376041600594218507.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also note how your right pinky finger – the smallest and weakest
finger you have – is supposed to handle 13 keys, just because the
whole layout is skewed that way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have struggled with this for years, because it simply doesn’t make
any sense — it’s easier to press the B key with right hand, and to
press the Y key with left, for example. Don’t even mention using the
correct finger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or another thing, the relative sizes of the keys. Originally typing
machines were powered by the muscles of the typist. And you needed to
use quite some force to get it to work properly. But the most force
was needed on the special keys that did something else than just swing
a tiny little hammer — the space bar, which moved the whole mechanism
forward, the enter key (or rather, lever), which scrolled the sheet of
paper, the shifts that moved the whole assembly up or down, and the
backspace. And if you look at the keyboard, those are the largest
keys. It’s because it was easier to press them with force when they
were bigger, but on a computer keyboard, where each key has the same
tiny switch underneath it makes no sense, maybe with the small
exception of the space bar, which needs to accommodate or famous
opposable thumbs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then there is the issue of the number of keys. Some typewriters had
separate keys for lower and for upper case letters — Linotype is one
famous machine that retained this design. Others introduced the
“shift”, which moved the whole mechanism a little, so that the second
set of symbols could be used. But there was still quite a lot of keys
needed, so traditional layouts have five rows of keys. On any touch-
typing lessons they tell you that your hands should rest on the so
called “home row” — where the F and J keys are, and only reach up or
down from there, without moving your wrist. But this is impossible for
most people with average finger length — to reach the number row you
already have to stretch, and reaching the functions keys or the Esc
key is practically impossible without moving your hands. There are too
many rows of keys! (And also all those keys to the right of the
keyboard, there is now way you can reach them with your poor pinky.)
Today we don’t need all those rows, we can have as many modifier keys
for switching layers as we want. In fact, we already have those Ctrl
and Alt and Super keys that we hardly ever use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then we have thumbs. I suspect the original designers of
typewriters must have had them severely atrophied, because the only
thing you were supposed to do with your strongest fingers was to press
the space bar. Which at first wasn’t even a key. All the other
modifier keys that are doing heavy lifting moving the whole mechanism
around are supposed to be pressed with your pinky fingers. Thumbs are
severely underused.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could keep going, but you probably already see where I’m going with
this. Most of those design decisions are unnecessary at best, and
harmful at worst today. Let’s get rid of them, and use mechanical
design that makes sense with modern technology. That means straight
columns, regularly sized keys, fewer rows, more modifier keys, and
keys operated with thumbs. That pretty much means Planck layout, or
something similar to that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-174917/images/1153521600596073975.png" src="projects/project-174917/images/1153521600596073975.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the layout I am currently using with my Dorsch 48k. It’s
loosely based on Planck, but with some small tweaks to make it more
similar to traditional keyboards (T-shaped arrow key block, Enter in
the correct position, two Shifts). Most importantly, this layout makes
it much easier to touch-type — in fact, you do it intuitively, because
there is simply no room to move your hands anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-174917/log-183829/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2020-09-20 in project-174917.</summary>
    <published>2020-09-20T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-174917/log-184226/</id>
    <title>Assembly</title>
    <updated>2020-09-29T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="assembly"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2020-09-29 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-174917/#project-174917"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Dorsch 48k Keyboard&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I forked this project from &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-174095/#project-174095"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Dorsch 40k Keyboard&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; , most of the technical details are there, so I thought it makes sense
to repeat it a little bit. I decided on a very minimal design — just
the PCB, no support plate and no case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-174917/images/4881121601368048825.jpg" src="projects/project-174917/images/4881121601368048825.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So this is basically just the PCB with the switches soldered directly
on it. The microcontroller had to be squeezed in there between the
switches, because the back needs to stay flat, so that I can cover it
with foam stickers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-174917/images/9357251601368175430.jpg" src="projects/project-174917/images/9357251601368175430.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They don’t look so great because I had to remove and re-attach them a
couple of times while I worked on the keyboard. They look much better
freshly applied, but I didn’t take that photo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the USB port didn’t fit between the keys, I decided to go with a
permanently attached USB cable. It’s soldered to the header, and then
glued to the PCB using a glue-soaked fabric ribbon, which also acts as
stress relief for the cable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-174917/images/8790051601368338578.jpg" src="projects/project-174917/images/8790051601368338578.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-174917/log-184226/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2020-09-29 in project-174917.</summary>
    <published>2020-09-29T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-174917/log-184227/</id>
    <title>Where are All the Keys?</title>
    <updated>2020-09-29T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="where-are-all-the-keys"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2020-09-29 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-174917/#project-174917"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Dorsch 48k Keyboard&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With just 47 keys on this keyboard, there has to be some trick for
getting all the missing keys somehow, so I’m going to try and explain
how the 40% layouts usually work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course the main trick is layers and layer switching keys. The
mechanism should be familiar from laptops or on-screen keyboards: you
have a special key, that, when pressed switches the keyboard into a
mode in which the keys have different functions than normally. This is
common for F1-F12 keys on laptops, or for media keys, but sometimes
even for keys like Home, End, PgUp and PgDn. On the 40% keyboards you
have to use this switching key pretty much for anything that us not a
letter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s look at an example. Here’s the layout of Dorsch 48k:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-174917/images/5222941601368923598.png" src="projects/project-174917/images/5222941601368923598.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The legends in the upper left corner of the keys are what you get if
you just simply press that key. They are usually all placed as close
to the original location of the given key on a “standard” keyboard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, suppose you want to type “1”. You look for it, and you see it’s
on the “Q” key, but in the lower right corner. That means you need to
press a function key, labelled “Raise”, and then the “Q” key. They
keyboard will act as if you pressed the “1” key.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what if you wanted to press “!”? You could press and hold “Raise”,
then press and hold “Shift” and then press “Q”, but that is a bit of
gimnastics, so the Planck layout that this layout is loosely based on
invented a shortcut: the “Lower” key, which is basically equivalent to
“Raise”+”Shift”. So to type “!” you simply press and hold “Lower” and
then press “Q”. This way you almost never have to press more than two
keys at once. The “Raise” and “Lower” keys are pressed with your
thumbs, so they don’t interfere with your regular typing movements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only problem is that you now how to learn where all the symbols
are again. But if you look carefully, you will notice that they are
pretty much in the same places as on a regular keyboard, only
compressed a little bit. So the top row is numbers, like on QWERTY,
with the minus and plus keys wrapped around. Quote and colon merged
together, question mark moved up one row, and square brackets got
pushed down a bit, but they now sit on the same keys as greater than
and lower than, so that’s easy to remember. Backslash is always a
problem, it landed in the only spot that was left.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the cursor movement keys are in their logical places too. Page up
and down are on up and down arrows, and Home and End are on the left
and right ones. Del and Ins got moved away a bit in this particular
layout, because I &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; need the right Alt key where it is, for
typing Polish accented characters. Normally Del would go there, so
it’s together with all the other cursor movement keys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still have some room for additional keys if I needed them.
Backspace, for example, could have a “lock screen” as a second
function. But I figured I will be adding those as I need them and get
used to the rest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-174917/log-184227/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2020-09-29 in project-174917.</summary>
    <published>2020-09-29T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>
