<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>http://deshipu.art/</id>
  <title>deshipu.art - Posts in project-8282</title>
  <updated>2024-08-07T20:31:02.279975+00:00</updated>
  <link href="http://deshipu.art/"/>
  <link href="http://deshipu.art/blog/category/project-8282/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://ablog.readthedocs.org/" version="0.10.33">ABlog</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-8282/log-27571/</id>
    <title>Laser Cutting</title>
    <updated>2015-11-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="laser-cutting"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2015-11-05 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-8282/#project-8282"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Alpen Clack&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is my second attempt at laser cutting, and it went much smoother
this time, in a large part due to help from the people at FabLab. I
generated the switch plate, and then used that as a base for the face
plate, back and the layers for the sides. I made a mistake that I
didn’t make the holes in the back plate a little bit smaller – so
that I could tap them and screw in the bolts into them directly, but I
think that I can fix it with some glue and a drill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-8282/images/5814551446753441061.jpg" src="projects/project-8282/images/5814551446753441061.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the keyboard is transparent, I will need to be much more careful
about soldering and generally cable routing, to make it look good. I
ordered a white A-Star module for the controller, mostly because it
has all the 26 pins broken out, but also because it’s white and will
look cool. I’m going to make it visible right over the arrow keys, and
to use the LEDs on it for the CapsLock and other indicators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also ordered some brown Gateron switches (they should look nice too,
as they have transparent cases), and some keycaps (they didn’t have
transparent ones), they should arrive in a couple of weeks and then I
can continue this project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-8282/log-27571/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2015-11-05 in project-8282.</summary>
    <published>2015-11-05T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-8282/log-27761/</id>
    <title>Metal Back</title>
    <updated>2015-11-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="metal-back"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2015-11-10 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-8282/#project-8282"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Alpen Clack&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the switches and keycaps will take their time to arrive, I’m
still working on the case. I have cut a back out of stainless steel
that I have found at the local hobby supplies store. Took 3 stone
wheel for my dremel clone, but it looks good enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-8282/images/3574471447186282897.jpg" src="projects/project-8282/images/3574471447186282897.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-8282/log-27761/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2015-11-10 in project-8282.</summary>
    <published>2015-11-10T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-8282/log-29165/</id>
    <title>Switches and Keycaps</title>
    <updated>2015-12-17T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="switches-and-keycaps"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2015-12-17 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-8282/#project-8282"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Alpen Clack&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Gateron switches and the keycaps that I ordered on Massdrop
finally arrived. The switches fit nicely:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-8282/images/4760751450349631799.jpg" src="projects/project-8282/images/4760751450349631799.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the with the keycaps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-8282/images/382361450349672885.jpg" src="projects/project-8282/images/382361450349672885.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still have two problems to solve, though. First, while the switches
fit, they are not particularry well kept in place by their snaps,
which apparently are designed for a thinner board. I will need to hold
them in place with something. Second, the acrylic sheet on which they
sit is really flimsy. I will either need to find something more
robust, or have them touch the back plate for stability. We will see
how it develops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-8282/log-29165/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2015-12-17 in project-8282.</summary>
    <published>2015-12-17T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-8282/log-29263/</id>
    <title>Electronics</title>
    <updated>2015-12-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="electronics"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2015-12-19 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-8282/#project-8282"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Alpen Clack&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I fixed the switches in place with a little bit of glue (they can
still be removed if needed), and I soldered the horizontal connections
with a thick copper wire. Then I drilled the mounting holes for the A*
board, and secured it in place with screws. I also drilled the hole
for the USB cable, cut the plug from it, passed it through the hole
and re-soldered a “naked” plug back. The board is mounted above the
arrow keys in such a way, that you can see the LEDs on it – I will
use those for CapsLock and so on. Finally, I taped the metal back-
plate with some transparent tape, so that there are no shorts, and
screwed it to the back – to make sure everything fits properly. The
keyboard got much sturdier now, and I think it won’t need additional
enforcing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-8282/images/6342241450545005077.jpg" src="projects/project-8282/images/6342241450545005077.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next step is soldering the SMD diodes and the vertical columns, then
connecting it all to the board, and modifying the firmware for this
particular layout. It’s almost finished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-8282/log-29263/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2015-12-19 in project-8282.</summary>
    <published>2015-12-19T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-8282/log-29420/</id>
    <title>Connections and Software</title>
    <updated>2015-12-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="connections-and-software"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2015-12-22 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-8282/#project-8282"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Alpen Clack&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So today I finished the second version of Alpen Clack – this one
built from scratch. As always, the most work-intensive part was
soldering everything together. This time I used non-insulated wire,
and added some kapton tape where it might touch anything – this was
much faster than removing the insulation from wires for soldering. The
finished connections, before closing the keyboard:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-8282/images/8888401450821121594.jpg" src="projects/project-8282/images/8888401450821121594.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next comes the programming. I used the same firmware as for version
one, except this time I had 6 columns and 17 rows (I kept the layout
rotated 90°, as this is much easier to fit in 80 columns of source
code). I also drilled a small hole for the reset button, to be able to
press it with a pin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Defining the layout was much easier this time, because of the saner
matrix – the Pololu A* Mini has enough pins broken out for me to not
care so much about saving them. Still, I miscalculated a little bit
and had to use one of the LED pins. That still left me two LEDs for
CapsLock and ScrollLock (no NumLock), so it’s fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once everything was ready, I spent the customary 4 hours tearing my
hair off and staring at the code, trying to debug a problem with it.
In the end, it turned out that the compiler was caching a little more
than it should, and recompiling everything from scratch solved it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-8282/log-29420/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2015-12-22 in project-8282.</summary>
    <published>2015-12-22T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>
