<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>http://deshipu.art/</id>
  <title>deshipu.art - Posts in project-19921</title>
  <updated>2024-08-07T20:31:58.533146+00:00</updated>
  <link href="http://deshipu.art/"/>
  <link href="http://deshipu.art/blog/category/project-19921/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://ablog.readthedocs.org/" version="0.10.33">ABlog</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-19921/log-170536/</id>
    <title>Time for a Refresh</title>
    <updated>2019-11-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="time-for-a-refresh"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2019-11-02 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-19921/#project-19921"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;SpiderWing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I left this project be, and focused more on the &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-158981&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-19603/#project-19603"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;D1 Mini Tote&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; projects, but it’s time to revisit it, and bring back the improvements
from those two projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-19921/log-170536/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2019-11-02 in project-19921.</summary>
    <published>2019-11-02T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-19921/log-170560/</id>
    <title>New PCB Design</title>
    <updated>2019-11-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="new-pcb-design"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2019-11-03 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-19921/#project-19921"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;SpiderWing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned, it’s time to modernize this design a little bit. So
first of all, I added the PCB legs from &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-19603/#project-19603"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;D1 Mini Tote&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; , and also added footprints for contact switches at the ends of those
legs. Then I switched all parts (except for headers) to SMD, because
that’s usually cheaper and easier to fabricate. Finally, we have some
additional headers for connecting those foot switches to the Feather’s
pins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-19921/images/1281951572805166234.png" src="projects/project-19921/images/1281951572805166234.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shield remains relatively simple — just a PCA9685 for servo
control, and a battery holder with a power switch, and a couple of
extra capacitors. The whole thing fits in 10x10cm, so you should be
able to order it easily, though some fabs might complain about
“multiple projects” in the design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-19921/log-170560/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2019-11-03 in project-19921.</summary>
    <published>2019-11-03T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-19921/log-171687/</id>
    <title>Batteries! Why Doesn’t Anybody Think About the Batteries?</title>
    <updated>2019-12-08T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="batteries-why-doesn-t-anybody-think-about-the-batteries"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2019-12-08 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-19921/#project-19921"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;SpiderWing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I decided that the new PCB design was lying on the disk long
enough, and that it’s time to order it. But then, when I opened it in
Fritzing, I decided to work on it a little bit more and add an
important feature: battery protection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You see, the batteries that Adafruit sells already come with the
protection circuit, so the battery handling circuit on the feathers
doesn’t include it, but those batteries are too small for all those
servos (and also kinda difficult to attach properly), so I’m instead
using a bare 16340 battery (it’s half of a 18650, if you were
wondering). But that means no protection, and that means you can
damage your batteries if you are forgetful. On the previous models I
had software monitoring of the battery status, but that’s not as
reliable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I decided to go on and add a battery protection chip. Looking
through my drawers, I found a HT3062E, which, judging by the Chinese
datasheet, should allow up to 8A of current — that should be plenty
for those tiny little servos. It comes in an ESPO8 package, so it was
easy enough to add it to the PCB design:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-19921/images/9019751575830955635.png" src="projects/project-19921/images/9019751575830955635.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had to remove the prototyping area at the front of the robot to make
room for it (it had to be close to the minus side of the battery), but
most Feathers have a prototyping area of their own on that side, so
that shouldn’t be too much of a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also made the pin header holes for the Feather staggered, so you
should be able to save some height of the robot by plugging the board
directly, without the need for female pin headers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ordered the boards from DirtyPCBs, because they are the only ones
who don’t care how many “designs” there are on a single PCB (most fabs
will treat all the leg parts as separate designs and demand additional
fees for them, for some reason).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-19921/log-171687/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2019-12-08 in project-19921.</summary>
    <published>2019-12-08T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-19921/log-171982/</id>
    <title>Bodgetty Bodge</title>
    <updated>2019-12-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="bodgetty-bodge"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2019-12-16 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-19921/#project-19921"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;SpiderWing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PCBs arrived today, so time for some testing. I didn’t have any
PCA9685 left, so I had to remove it from one of my old  &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-13278/#project-13278"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Servo Breakout for WeMos D1 Mini&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; boards. With all the parts in place, time for some test:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-19921/images/4958321576536384211.jpg" src="projects/project-19921/images/4958321576536384211.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And nope, the Feather doesn’t get enough power. That’s weird. Let’s
check the footprint for that battery protection chip again, shall we?
Ah-ha! Here you go, I switched two pins, of course:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-19921/images/7309481576536451260.jpg" src="projects/project-19921/images/7309481576536451260.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately the bodge is quite easy here. Of course I already fixed
the mistake in the PCB design files. With this small change,
everything is working as intended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took some time to assemble the legs, but nothing revolutionary
there. I have all the physical parts assembled, but no time for tuning
and programming it, so it will probably wait for the holidays.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-19921/images/4893731576536584771.jpg" src="projects/project-19921/images/4893731576536584771.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-19921/log-171982/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2019-12-16 in project-19921.</summary>
    <published>2019-12-16T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-19921/log-172522/</id>
    <title>It’s Alive (Again)</title>
    <updated>2019-12-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="it-s-alive-again"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2019-12-31 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-19921/#project-19921"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;SpiderWing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took me a while to re-assemble, re-connect and re-calibrate all the
legs with the new PCB, but today the robot is again standing on its
own. I was a bit worried that the battery protection circuit would
interfere with the servos drawing their share of the current, but it
seems to be perfectly fine. I was putting off connecting the servos
for a bit, because I didn’t have the male pin headers soldered, and I
was thinking that perhaps I should cut the servo wires and solder them
directly to the underside of the PCB. But then I decided to leave them
long for now, for easier hacking. I can always make a “tidy” version
of this robot later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-19921/images/8232111577816509284.JPG" src="projects/project-19921/images/8232111577816509284.JPG" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have replaced the old HUZZAH feather with the new NRF52840 feather,
because the CircuitPython is no longer supported on the ESP8266, and
there is some very exciting progresss on bluetooth support on the NRF,
and that would be perfect for controlling this robot. For now I just
use the REPL over the USB cable, though, still using the old gait code
— that’s one of the parts that still needs work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also still no switches at the ends of the legs — they are
ordered, but Christmas is not the time of fast packages. At the very
least they should let the robot avoid falling off the table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see, since I’m using stacking headers with all my feathers,
there is room for adding modules on top of the robot. It could be a
prototyping board with some sensors, or one of the other featherwings
with displays, LEDs, speakers, etc. — it would even work very well
with the &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-165011&lt;/span&gt; , controlled by gestures — if I ever get that to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-19921/log-172522/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2019-12-31 in project-19921.</summary>
    <published>2019-12-31T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>
