<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>http://deshipu.art/</id>
  <title>deshipu.art - Posted in 2018</title>
  <updated>2024-08-07T20:37:32.167631+00:00</updated>
  <link href="http://deshipu.art/"/>
  <link href="http://deshipu.art/blog/2018/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://ablog.readthedocs.org/" version="0.10.33">ABlog</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-160167/log-154978/</id>
    <title>What I Hope to Achieve?</title>
    <updated>2018-10-21T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="what-i-hope-to-achieve"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2018-10-21 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../projects/project-160167/#project-160167"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Electronic Barrette Hub&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s time to talk a little bit about the goals of this project.  On
the face of it, there is really very little creativity in it: it’s
basically just a carrier PCB for the Circuit Playground Express board,
with a battery, charger and some connectors. You can build three
projects like that before breakfast. There is absolutely nothing novel
or revolutionary or technically challenging in here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, I am not aware of anything like this already
existing, and I am convinced that and existence of something like this
would be extremely useful for a lot of people. Not just for beginners,
who are afraid to try soldering, or designing a PCB like this, but
also experienced wearable builders and cosplayers, who don’t need to
reinvent the wheel every time, and can simply build their stuff around
an already existing design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you look at, say, Arduino, it wasn’t a “revolutionary” project
either. Every single thing on it has been done before multiple times
and was widely available. But Arduino made it easier for everyone by
bringing those things together in one package, and creating a standard
platform to build on, sharing and re-mixing your designs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A bare microcontroller board lets you build anything — the
possibilities are infinite, and mind staggers confronted with a blank
page. A base like the Barrette Hub limits your freedom and suggests
what to build — making it much easier to begin, and hopefully bringing
more people into the wonderful world of interactive wearables. Later
on, when you are more experienced, you can leave it for other, more
flexible and universal solutions, but you will probably still come
back when your particular use case is a good fit, and a ready solution
can save you time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Will it work? Will the platform become popular? Will the idea catch
on? Will it become an actual standard? I have no idea, this is very
much a question of luck and of appearing at just the right time and
place. I believe the right time for this kind of platform is closing
in fast, and I am willing to do the work to give it a try. Time will
tell if it’s a wasted effort or not, but in the worst case I still
learn a lot in the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-160167/log-154978/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2018-10-21 in project-160167.</summary>
    <published>2018-10-21T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-160167/log-155074/</id>
    <title>Proper Prototype</title>
    <updated>2018-10-22T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="proper-prototype"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2018-10-22 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../projects/project-160167/#project-160167"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Electronic Barrette Hub&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PCBs just arrived from &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://hackaday.io/hacker/131216"&gt;&amp;#64;oshpark &lt;/a&gt; and I finally assembled a proper prototype. I’m quite happy with how
it looks, even without the face plate or any ornaments on the PCB:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-160167/images/1804971540204588238.jpg" src="projects/project-160167/images/1804971540204588238.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In particular, I like how the holes covered with the soldermask look
like: inconspicious. I used staggered holes for the connectors, which
means that you can simply insert male pin headers into them — you can
see one inserted in the top right corner. That really lets me hide
them from view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are five connectors:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-160167/images/7089001540204735865.jpg" src="projects/project-160167/images/7089001540204735865.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Four for general purpose GPIO pins, with two pins on each, also
doubling for UART and I2C communication, and one for USB, for those
devices (like the &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../projects/project-158701/#project-158701"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Video Pendant&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; ) which are too small to fit an USB port, but still need USB
communication. The power on the USB port is stabilized 3.3V, while the
remaining ports are connected to the battery directly, because they
are likely to need all the power they can get.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will do some more testing with those connectors, and if they don’t
work well enough, I will solder either female pin headers, or grove
sockets in there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More importantly, the build instructions and parts list are now
updated, and there is a bunch of new photos. Unfortunately I won’t
have time to update the video, but the basic functionality shown there
remains the same (well, except for the battery charging, but that’s a
boring thing to watch).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next step will be working on the ornaments and the face plate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-160167/log-155074/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2018-10-22 in project-160167.</summary>
    <published>2018-10-22T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-21578/log-155174/</id>
    <title>Replaced by PewPew Standalone</title>
    <updated>2018-10-23T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="replaced-by-pewpew-standalone"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2018-10-23 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../projects/project-21578/#project-21578"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;PewPew FeatherWing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this still works and is fully compatible with all other PewPew
boards, and while I still sell it on Tindie, check out the new devices
over at &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../projects/project-159733/#project-159733"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;PewPew Standalone&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; — they are bigger and cheaper, though no color display.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-21578/log-155174/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2018-10-23 in project-21578.</summary>
    <published>2018-10-23T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-159022/log-156989/</id>
    <title>Soon…</title>
    <updated>2018-12-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="soon"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2018-12-12 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../projects/project-159022/#project-159022"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Rainbow Jellyfish&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-159022/images/9979701544611627927.jpg" src="projects/project-159022/images/9979701544611627927.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-159022/log-156989/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2018-12-12 in project-159022.</summary>
    <published>2018-12-12T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-158981/log-157389/</id>
    <title>Immediate Plans</title>
    <updated>2018-12-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="immediate-plans"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2018-12-21 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../projects/project-158981/#project-158981"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Kubik M0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had a bit of a break with this project, while I worked on other
projects and dealt with some life stuff, but I very much still want to
work on it. Obviously the very next step that needs to be done is to
program the robot to do actual walking, at least at the level of &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../projects/project-6050/#project-6050"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Tote&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; , and then possibly make use of the accelerometer and the leg
switches. I assume that this will actually take me some time. In the
mean time, CircuitPython is being developed further and ported to the
NRF52 chip, growing bluetooth support along the way, so the long-term
plan is to switch to NRF52 from the SAMD21 chip. That will probably
involve a redesign of the extension connector as well, so I don’t
think I will be working on any extensions until that happens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the connector design is finalized, it will be time to look at
possible extensions and the sensors to include on them. I want to have
an OpenMV adapter, and also a simple “face” with distance sensors on
it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-158981/log-157389/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2018-12-21 in project-158981.</summary>
    <published>2018-12-21T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>
