<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>http://deshipu.art/</id>
  <title>deshipu.art - Posted in 2014</title>
  <updated>2024-08-07T20:46:57.087621+00:00</updated>
  <link href="http://deshipu.art/"/>
  <link href="http://deshipu.art/blog/2014/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://ablog.readthedocs.org/" version="0.10.33">ABlog</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-3301/log-11652/</id>
    <title>Rubber Paint and Blue Smoke</title>
    <updated>2014-12-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="rubber-paint-and-blue-smoke"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2014-12-06 in &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-3301&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I still didn’t get to get the camera modules to stream any
video, I worked a little bit on the servo controller and mechanical
parts of the robot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For one, I discovered why all the frequencies were half what I
expected from the code – I selected the 5V, not 3.3V board in the
Arduino IDE, so the code was compiled for the wrong model. Selecting
the right board fixes all those issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing is the voltage monitor. I added a simple voltage divider
on two resistors, and connected it to one of the analog pins on the
servo controller. Now I can shut down the servos if the battery
voltage reaches a critical level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also painted the servo horns at the ends of the legs with some
rubber paint, hoping that will let them get a better grip on the
floor. Unfortunately, it seems to have very little effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, when testing the new servo controller code, I must have
shorted one of the cables, and my servo controller released blue
smoke. As you all know, those electronic components are actually
powered by magical blue smoke inside, and if you release it, they stop
working. I’m considering using a 5V one now, because I’ve run out of
3.3V replacements…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Update: So, after some research, it turns out that the part that got
fried is… the on/off switch. Phew. That’s literally the cheapest
part, so I’m lucky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-3301/log-11652/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2014-12-06 in project-3301.</summary>
    <published>2014-12-06T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-3301/log-12113/</id>
    <title>More Blue Smoke</title>
    <updated>2014-12-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="more-blue-smoke"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2014-12-23 in &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-3301&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today is a sad day for this project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to use a new battery that I bought specially for this robot,
instead of using battery packs from my Walkera RC helicopter. Taught
with previous mistakes, I have a socket for the battery that only lets
you insert the plug the correct way. Being assured by this, I didn’t
really look carefully when I connected the battery… Alerted by the
hissing and smoke from the power switch, I immediately disconnected it
but… too late.\&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What happened? Look at this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-3301/images/8281741419344482332.jpg" src="projects/project-3301/images/8281741419344482332.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See? Battery packs from different manufacturers have the plugs in
reverse… I suppose that increases their sales.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, this time not only the power switch is fried – also
the VoCore. The Arduino Pro Mini and the camera module seem to be
fine, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-3301/log-12113/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2014-12-23 in project-3301.</summary>
    <published>2014-12-23T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-3300/log-12121/</id>
    <title>One More Sensor</title>
    <updated>2014-12-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="one-more-sensor"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2014-12-23 in &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-3300&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I still can’t get myself to write the code for using the
accelerometer+gyroscope properly, I did recently do a small
modification to this robot. I got myself a bunch of coin-sized 3A
voltage regulators, so I replaced the UBEC that I used in this robot
with one of those. That, together with shorter wires, saved me some
space inside, which I used to add a Sharp distance sensor, and to
position the accelerometer module a little better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-3300/images/1378261419370980391.jpg" src="projects/project-3300/images/1378261419370980391.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I can at least try to write some simple obstacle avoidance code…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-3300/log-12121/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2014-12-23 in project-3300.</summary>
    <published>2014-12-23T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-3694/log-12194/</id>
    <title>Ready to Program</title>
    <updated>2014-12-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="ready-to-program"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2014-12-27 in &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-3694&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This robot took me two days to build from scratch, but I’m pretty
happy with it already. I think it’s pretty much finished mechanically
(only missing some rubber endings on the legs). Software-wise, I have
ported my maestro controller library to Micropython, so I can already
move the individual servos from the REPL console of the PyBoard, over
USB. The next step will be to port the inverse kinematics code, adjust
it to take into consideration that there are six legs now and that
they are at various angles to the body, and then make it walk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-3694/log-12194/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2014-12-27 in project-3694.</summary>
    <published>2014-12-27T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-3694/log-12251/</id>
    <title>Moving a Leg and Making Sounds</title>
    <updated>2014-12-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="moving-a-leg-and-making-sounds"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2014-12-29 in &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-3694&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The software for the basic inverse kinematics is going slowly, mostly
because I’m reorganizing the code that I already used in all the other
robots, with a goal of making a library of it. In the meantime, I had
a little distraction: I added the buzzer to a DAC pin of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://micropython.org"&gt;PyBoard&lt;/a&gt; , and it turns out it’s fast enough to &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://micropython.org/doc/tut-amp-skin"&gt;play WAV files&lt;/a&gt; ! After some mucking around with the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://theportalwiki.com/wiki/Turret_voice_lines"&gt;turret lines from Portal&lt;/a&gt; , I finally used &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://bfxr.net"&gt;bfxr&lt;/a&gt;  to generate some simple bleeps and pews, and then &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://libav.org/avconv.html"&gt;avconv&lt;/a&gt;  to concert them to 8bit, 11025 rate files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A video showing that I have control over the servos and the speaker:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe style="width: 500px; height: 281px;" width="500" height="281" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/KuDnKCzzc0Q"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-3694/log-12251/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2014-12-29 in project-3694.</summary>
    <published>2014-12-29T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>
