<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>http://deshipu.art/</id>
  <title>deshipu.art - Posts in project-174982</title>
  <updated>2024-08-07T20:45:04.307297+00:00</updated>
  <link href="http://deshipu.art/"/>
  <link href="http://deshipu.art/blog/category/project-174982/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://ablog.readthedocs.org/" version="0.10.33">ABlog</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-174982/log-184354/</id>
    <title>The Tricky DPI</title>
    <updated>2020-10-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="the-tricky-dpi"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2020-10-01 in &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-174982&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember how I mentioned that I like this layout, but the keys could
be a bit closer together, and blamed the angles of the columns for
them being too far apart? Turns out the columns are perfectly fine,
the keyboard is just scaled up roughly 10%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How did that happen?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, for designing the PCB outline, and for marking the desired
locations of the switches I used Inkscape. I made sure all dimensions
were correct in that program, using the handy unit switching options
that program has. But as it turns out, Inkscape was recently updated
on my computer, and the new version uses different DPI in the SVG
files it saves than the older one, and than what Fritzing assumes on
import. But it was consistent, so the part outlines exported from
Fritzing didn’t get resized, thus the holes for the switches fit fine.
The whole keyboard is just larger than it was supposed to be. The
angled keys only made it difficult to confirm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I only discovered this just now, while working on the &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-175043&lt;/span&gt; design. Sure enough, the same thing happened there, so I had to
practically re-do all the routing. Thanks Obama.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-174982/log-184354/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2020-10-01 in project-174982.</summary>
    <published>2020-10-01T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-174982/log-184987/</id>
    <title>One More Try</title>
    <updated>2020-10-13T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="one-more-try"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2020-10-13 in &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-174982&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project has been a bit unlucky from the beginning. Not only it is
a continuation of a failed project, which brought its own problems,
but I’ve been really sloppy with the execution as well. I decided to
get mu stuff together a little bit more and give this layout a fair
chance this time. So I’m going to make this keyboard, at a proper
scale and with known good switches. It will be 2mm higher because of
that, but it will be comfortable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This keyboard is driven by three main goals:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;a reasonably complete keyboard with digits and arrows that is low-
profile,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;with an ergonomic, one-piece split layout,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;ortholinear.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project was most inspired with something called the TGR Alice
keyboard, designed by Yuk Tsi:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-174982/images/723351602617205799.jpg" src="projects/project-174982/images/723351602617205799.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is simply something very elegant in the way he compromised
between the available keycaps, the traditional layout, and the needs
of ergonomy. I love how this looks, however, I learned that layouts
with staggered rows like this make it harder for me to touch-type. I
want an ortholinear layout, where the keys are arranged in a grid, or
at least into columns for each of the fingers. The original Turbot
layout was an attempt to create something like that, mostly based on
the Atreus layout and some other ergonomic keyboards, trying to make
the gaps between keys manageable by angling each column at a different
angle. But if you look carefully at that Alice keyboard, that is not
what they did there. Instead, you have three sections of the keyboard,
each angled differently, but otherwise following the traditional
layout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what if I took an ortholinear keyboard instead, but then repeated
the operations they did with Alice on that? I came up with something
like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-174982/images/7548101602617589288.png" src="projects/project-174982/images/7548101602617589288.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a little busier than Alice, mostly because there are more keys on
the bottom row, and because the grids of the ortholinear parts are
very strong visual cues, so it is not as elegant, but it should be
equally or even more convenient. This time I didn’t stagger the
columns—except for the ones for the little fingers, which are
naturally about half a key lower, due to the angling. That should work
well with the fact that the little finger is shorter in most people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also removed some of the extra keys Turbot originally had on the
sides—since I need a “function” key anyways for Fn keys, I can as well
put them on a separate layer, together with all the media keys and
such. Thanks to that the PCB also has a much more “normal” shape:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-174982/images/6515131602618201989.png" src="projects/project-174982/images/6515131602618201989.png" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-174982/images/495111602618211309.png" src="projects/project-174982/images/495111602618211309.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can tell that I didn’t really take my time to route the traces
nicely and make them all bend at 45° angle, as they should. The reason
is that with the modern fabrication methods it doesn’t really matter,
and I was in a hurry to add this PCB to an already ongoing order at
JLCPCB, so that they can be shipped together. You see, they let you do
that, and since there was a National day, my order didn’t ship yet, so
I used the chance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have now made a version of that PCB with nicer traces and with some
holes for mounting stabilizers, I will make it available if this PCB
works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still had some free pins, so I added a single LED and a joystick,
with some extra keys in the middle — maybe I will make it emulate
mouse too, we will see. In the worst case I will leave those
unpopulated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note about key caps: I am going to use the same key caps I initially
got for Flounder, and they are a bit of a strange set. This layout is
designed specially for those key caps. All keys are either 1U, 1.5U or
2U, except for the Ctrl keys, which for some reason are 1.25U. More
common key caps usually have more of the .25U keys, since the two
bottom alphanumeric rows are staggered by 0.25U, but not on the
keyboard those key caps were made for. I have no idea why they did
that. The short version is, that if you plan to use any key caps from
a normal keyboard, you will have to modify this design somewhat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, since I’m waiting for the PCB anyways, I also took some time one
evening to think about the precise location of the keys on the other
layer. I came up with something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-174982/images/5913311602618854663.png" src="projects/project-174982/images/5913311602618854663.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I might still move the arrow cluster on the left hand side, to make it
a more standard WASD, but I’m not sure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-174982/log-184987/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2020-10-13 in project-174982.</summary>
    <published>2020-10-13T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-174982/log-185055/</id>
    <title>Stab Stab Stab</title>
    <updated>2020-10-16T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="stab-stab-stab"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2020-10-16 in &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-174982&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stabs, or what normal people call stabilizers, are special levers
added under any key longer than 1.5U to make sure that the key goes
down evenly no matter which part of it you are pressing. Many keyboard
designs avoid longer keys just to avoid dealing with stabs, but here
we don’t really have much choice: Turbot has 4 keys that are 2U long,
and that is already long enough to warrant stabs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Flounder I tested several commercially available types of
stabilizers, but they were all either incompatible with low-profile
keys, or required space on the underside of the PCB — which doesn’t
work when the PCB is supposed to lie flat on the desk. So I went ahead
and made my own stabilizers out of paperclips, using the holes in the
PCB to mount them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time I didn’t make any holes for attaching the stabilizers and I
plan to do something else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Commercial keyboards that use the Kailh choc switches have a very neat
solution for this problem:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-174982/images/2998901602854753868.jpg" src="projects/project-174982/images/2998901602854753868.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tops of the switches have a special groove to hold the lever.
Unfortunately, you can’t easily buy switches like that, so I decided
to try and make my own. I started by using a bad PCB from another
project to make a drilling jig:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-174982/images/8687651602854866117.jpg" src="projects/project-174982/images/8687651602854866117.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using that jig I can drill holes in the case of the switch on both
sides, and then put a paperclip through it. Since I only have 2U keys
at most, I will not need those extra bits on the sides. I still need
something for the paperclip to hook onto, though, but that was already
a solved problem in Flounder:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-174982/images/7843951602855055027.jpg" src="projects/project-174982/images/7843951602855055027.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simply glue some pieces of wire to underside of the key caps, and
done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-174982/log-185055/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2020-10-16 in project-174982.</summary>
    <published>2020-10-16T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-174982/log-185271/</id>
    <title>Only Missing Switches</title>
    <updated>2020-10-20T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="only-missing-switches"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2020-10-20 in &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-174982&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PCBs came, and they seem fine. I decided to add some diagonal
strips to one, with a can of spray paint, just for the kicks. Also
soldered all the diodes and the chip, so all that is missing are the
switches, which are still on the boat from China somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-174982/images/2954841603197999004.jpg" src="projects/project-174982/images/2954841603197999004.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, happy to report that the scale is correct this time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-174982/log-185271/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2020-10-20 in project-174982.</summary>
    <published>2020-10-20T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-174982/log-185474/</id>
    <title>First Tests</title>
    <updated>2020-10-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="first-tests"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2020-10-27 in &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-174982&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have the switches, I assembled the keyboard and testing can now
begin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-174982/images/9221811603756753975.jpg" src="projects/project-174982/images/9221811603756753975.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, after about a month of using a Planck keyboard, this
feels huge. I can no longer reach the backspace or esc keys without
moving my hands, which is going to affect my touch-typing a bit, I
suppose, unless I remap them to those extra keys in the middle, maybe?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The switches are great, the proportions of the keyboard are fine, and
the layout seems to be working fine. All the keys are where I expect
them. The right shift could be a bit bigger, but then there would be
no room for the arrow keys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m going to use this keyboard for a while now, and see how well it
works for text, code, computer games and graphics programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m also uploading the design files and the ukeeb example for it, in
case someone wants to try it themselves. The design files are updated,
with nicer, less angular traces and with one missing connection for
the center keys added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-174982/log-185474/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2020-10-27 in project-174982.</summary>
    <published>2020-10-27T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>
