<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>http://deshipu.art/</id>
  <title>deshipu.art - Posts in project-171381</title>
  <updated>2024-08-07T20:33:02.443217+00:00</updated>
  <link href="http://deshipu.art/"/>
  <link href="http://deshipu.art/blog/category/project-171381/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://ablog.readthedocs.org/" version="0.10.33">ABlog</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-171381/log-180103/</id>
    <title>Version 1.3 Testing</title>
    <updated>2020-07-02T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="version-1-3-testing"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2020-07-02 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-171381/#project-171381"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Fluff M0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-171381/images/1574421593703185668.jpg" src="projects/project-171381/images/1574421593703185668.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PCBs arrived after their 3-week trip around the Europe, and as
usual I assembled and tested one. The good news is that it works very
well with any USB-A to USB-C cable. The plug is a bit wobbly, because
there is no metal sleeve to stabilize it, but it doesn’t disconnect or
otherwise cause problems. The CNC router was even precise enough to
mill the small teeth on the sides of the socket, so it goes in with a
slight click. I’m pretty happy with that.\&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bad news is that it completely fails to work when connected to an
actual USB-C socket with a proper USB-C cable. It simply doesn’t
receive any power. A little bit of research easily explains why: I
didn’t add pull-downs on the CC1 and CC2 pins, because I thought it’s
only needed for OTG devices. Turns out that the wording is a bit
confusing, and it’s required to have those resistors for USB 2.0
device to receive any power from an USB-C port.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That means there will be version 1.4 of the board, and it means the
parts count also raises — I need to squeeze 2 more resistors in there.
I could probably get away with just one resistor — only one of CC1 or
CC2 is ever connected — but I will make room for two, and use a bodge
wire to see if it works also with one — I will need fewer prototypes
that way.\&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-171381/log-180103/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2020-07-02 in project-171381.</summary>
    <published>2020-07-02T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-171381/log-180508/</id>
    <title>Version 1.4</title>
    <updated>2020-07-09T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="version-1-4"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2020-07-09 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-171381/#project-171381"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Fluff M0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the fail with missing pulld-downs on CC pins for USB-C, I re-
designed the board a little bit:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-171381/images/9170771594311980013.png" src="projects/project-171381/images/9170771594311980013.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are now contacts and pull-downs for the CC pins, and I also
added a large prototyping area in the empty part of the board. The
holes are now just on the silkscreen. This time the boards arrived in
a few days:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-171381/images/2936651594312097316.jpg" src="projects/project-171381/images/2936651594312097316.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I put the address of my website on the other side, so that I can use
the very flat board as a kind of business card:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-171381/images/8593701594312139405.jpg" src="projects/project-171381/images/8593701594312139405.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s pretty much it. The new version works perfectly fine both with
USB 2.0 and actual USB-C ports. I’m publishing the fritzing design
file, the gerbers and the BOM, so that anyone can make their own — you
can find them in the downloads section of this page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-171381/log-180508/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2020-07-09 in project-171381.</summary>
    <published>2020-07-09T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-171381/log-180917/</id>
    <title>Micro-USB</title>
    <updated>2020-07-17T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="micro-usb"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2020-07-17 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-171381/#project-171381"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Fluff M0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last version is all correct — it has all the pins in the right
places, the USB-C socket works well with the pull-down resistors in
place, there is a large prototyping area and the staggered pin holes.
Not much left to improve. However, if I think about the original goal
of being a cheap replacement for the Feather M0 Basic to be left in
projects or used for workshop, there is still some room for
improvement, so I decided to try one more time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, black silkscreen with yellow soldermask is uncommon
combination (which is a damn shame, it looks much better than white
silkscreen, and they use black silkscreen for white soldermask already
anyways), so to get the cheesy looks I would need to pay extra for the
uncommon color combination. So if I used a decoration that works well
with other colors, I could save here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, USB-C cables are expensive, and USB-C ports are usually only
on new and expensive devices. If I organize a workshop, I want it to
be available for everyone, and not just the rich kids — so I would
have to provide USB-C to USB-A cables (expensive). However, the same
technique as used for the USB-C socket can be also used for the Micro-
USB socket — you won’t get the satisfying click when the plug is
inserted, but otherwise it should work the same. And I can ditch the
two resistors then!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, the prototyping area on the Feather M0 Basic has some
additional rails for power — that would be useful and help avoid some
cable mess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I designed this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-171381/images/9382171594990082794.png" src="projects/project-171381/images/9382171594990082794.png" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-171381/images/277211594990091459.png" src="projects/project-171381/images/277211594990091459.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This version is a little bit more obviously Swiss, uses micro-USB
socket, and has a prototyping area with power rails and some extra
pads in it for squeezing SMD components in there. It also has the LED
in a position a little bit more similar to where original Feathers
have it, and a second prototyping area where the battery socket
normally goes. Otherwise it’s all the same stuff as previously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PCBs are ordered and I will be testing the prototypes as soon as
they arrive. I will publish the designs if they test fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-171381/log-180917/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2020-07-17 in project-171381.</summary>
    <published>2020-07-17T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-171381/log-181174/</id>
    <title>Version 1.5</title>
    <updated>2020-07-22T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="version-1-5"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2020-07-22 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-171381/#project-171381"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Fluff M0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PCBs for the micro-USB version arrived:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-171381/images/6853911595411016973.jpg" src="projects/project-171381/images/6853911595411016973.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some notes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The connector works. Yay.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s a little bit tight thickness-wise. More on that below.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I made it a little too deep — I can make it about 1.5mm smaller.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s strong, even with the vias all lined up like that (later version
has the vias more spread). It shouldn’t break off.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is a bit of sideways wobble possible, but it doesn’t seem to
cause any connection problems.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The width of the cutout is just right.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The pad on the top of the connector, that was supposed to connect to
the shield, is useless, and can cause a short if the plug is inserted
wrong way around.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’m happy with the prototyping areas, I’m going to leave them like
that.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The connector doesn’t necessarily look like an USB connector, so I’m
going to add a label to it describing it as such.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The staggering of the contacts, so that power gets connected before
the signals, is superfluous, because they are already staggered in the
plug. I will remove that.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, speaking about the thickness of the connector, it seems to be on
the edge of acceptable. The first insertion requires a bit of force
and leaves marks on the contacts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-171381/images/4250601595411886408.jpg" src="projects/project-171381/images/4250601595411886408.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This seems to be mostly to the thickness added by the HASL process of
coating the contacts with solder. I hope that removing the pad from
the other side will improve the situation here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of the board thickness, I also made some 0.8mm PCBs for the
USB-C version, and it does sit in the plug much better, while still
not being too tight, so that is the preferred thickness for that kind
of connector for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-171381/log-181174/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2020-07-22 in project-171381.</summary>
    <published>2020-07-22T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-171381/log-181344/</id>
    <title>Pinout</title>
    <updated>2020-07-25T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="pinout"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2020-07-25 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-171381/#project-171381"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Fluff M0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To actually do something with a board, it’s good to know which pin
does what. The Feather standard already defines the functions of some
pins, but they can do so much more. So here is a pinout with the most
useful pin functions documented:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-171381/images/9063121595704910506.png" src="projects/project-171381/images/9063121595704910506.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially I tried to figure it all out from the datasheet, but I
quickly noticed it’s non-trivial. Some timers and some sercoms are
used internally by CircuitPython, and some are not available in the
version of the chip I’m using. So instead I decided to take a brute
force approach, and wrote a simple program that just tries all the
possible combinations.\&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, when it came to PWM, I simply gave up. The number of
combinations is huge, especially since order of creating the PWM
outputs matters, so I’m simply just marking which pins can have PWM at
all. It’s up to the user to check if the particular combination of
pins they want to use for PWM is viable. I simply can’t think of a way
to present this information clearly in a graphical way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-171381/log-181344/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2020-07-25 in project-171381.</summary>
    <published>2020-07-25T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>
