<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>http://deshipu.art/</id>
  <title>deshipu.art - Posts in project-167897</title>
  <updated>2024-08-07T20:46:55.203308+00:00</updated>
  <link href="http://deshipu.art/"/>
  <link href="http://deshipu.art/blog/category/project-167897/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://ablog.readthedocs.org/" version="0.10.33">ABlog</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-167897/log-169613/</id>
    <title>The Swiss Mechanical Keyboard Enthusiasts Meetup</title>
    <updated>2019-10-04T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="the-swiss-mechanical-keyboard-enthusiasts-meetup"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2019-10-04 in &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-167897&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It all started on a Sunday, when I brought my &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-8282&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-10408&lt;/span&gt; projects to the sixth keyboard pervs meetup. I had my eyes on the low-
profile Kailh switches since a while, but their official website only
lets you order a bag of 800 pieces at the minimum, and I didn’t have
the energy to go out and organize a group buy. I even brought my
KB390L keyboard that uses those switches, that is my favorite keyboard
since two years, and that I use daily. But I saw very few keyboards
using those switches, except for this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-167897/images/2136131570216450484.JPG" src="projects/project-167897/images/2136131570216450484.JPG" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-167897/images/2891091570216475643.JPG" src="projects/project-167897/images/2891091570216475643.JPG" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I loved the minimalist approach to those keyboards ( &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://oddrocketkeyboards.blogspot.com/2018/05/5plit-v2.html"&gt;called 5plit&lt;/a&gt; ), the chocolate switches they use, and the fact that they use the
same PCB for both halves, just flipped over. And the PCB fits in
10x10cm, so it’s cheap to manufacture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I met the author of this keyboard, and learned that he uses it for his
everyday keyboarding needs, even though it started as just a silly
experiment. Sounds really great. I asked if he could sell any spare
PCBs, and he did, so now I have a pair of them. He also told me about
the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://kailh.aliexpress.com"&gt;Aliexpress shop that Kailh has&lt;/a&gt; , where you can buy those and other switches in any quantity you want.
Also key caps and everything else. So I made the order the same day,
for 40 switches and as many transparent key caps, to bring this
keyboard to life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today the switches and key caps arrived. I still have the diodes, the
jack sockets and cable, and one of the pro micros (I ran out) on
order, so it probably won’t be ready until next month (I go on
vacation too).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-167897/images/6524061570216968941.jpg" src="projects/project-167897/images/6524061570216968941.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-167897/log-169613/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2019-10-04 in project-167897.</summary>
    <published>2019-10-04T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-167897/log-169614/</id>
    <title>Up Side Down Handheld Keyboard</title>
    <updated>2019-10-04T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="up-side-down-handheld-keyboard"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2019-10-04 in &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-167897&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One project that I was thinking about since a while is a reversed
keyboard, that goes on the back of a tablet or phone (or any other
device with a screen), so that you can use it with all your fingers
while holding the device. I realized, that if I just soldered the
thumb keys on the other side of 5plit, I could make such a keyboard:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-167897/images/1175901570217203513.JPG" src="projects/project-167897/images/1175901570217203513.JPG" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just imagine a tablet velcroed on top of this. I am still not sure I
really want to do this, but I’m really curious why nobody does it. It
seems such an obvious solution, that there must be some catch that I’m
not seeing. Anybody wants to save me the effort and reveal it for me?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure I will do it, but it is very tempting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-167897/log-169614/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2019-10-04 in project-167897.</summary>
    <published>2019-10-04T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-167897/log-170331/</id>
    <title>Waiting for Diodes</title>
    <updated>2019-10-27T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="waiting-for-diodes"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2019-10-27 in &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-167897&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the components slowly arrived, and now I only have one thing
missing: the diodes for de-ghosting the keys. Unfortunately, this
design uses through-hole diodes, and I only have SMD ones in my
drawers, because I avoid through-hole parts whenever I can. So I had
to order them, and they take a long time. I guess in the worst case I
could solder some wires to the SMD diodes, but I don’t really feel
like doing that for 36 diodes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-167897/images/6911231572207959428.jpg" src="projects/project-167897/images/6911231572207959428.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While waiting for the diodes, I should probably start looking into
programming the pro micros with the right firmware.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-167897/log-170331/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2019-10-27 in project-167897.</summary>
    <published>2019-10-27T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-167897/log-170457/</id>
    <title>Programming and Layout</title>
    <updated>2019-11-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="programming-and-layout"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2019-11-01 in &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-167897&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The diodes actually arrived the next day, and I soldered up
everything, but I didn’t have the energy to program it, so I let it
sit there for a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-167897/images/6385351572563756594.jpg" src="projects/project-167897/images/6385351572563756594.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today evening I finally decided to look into programming it. It turns
out that there is actually a repository for this keyboard on github,
with a ready configuration for the qmk firmware for it (there are also
the Gerber files for the PCB there):  &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/larrbo/odd-rocket/tree/master/5plit%20-kailh"&gt;https://github.com/larrbo/odd-rocket/tree/master/5plit%20-kailh&lt;/a&gt; \&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way you use it, you first need to get the firmware from &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/qmk/qmk_firmware"&gt;https://github.com/qmk/qmk_firmware&lt;/a&gt;  and then copy the keyboard definition file to the
“keyboards” directory. Then just run “make 5plit:default” to compile
it, and “make 5plit:default:flash” to flash it — reset the pro micro
when it tells you to. You have to program both pro micros, and the one
that has the USB connected is the left one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The default layout looks something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-167897/images/6468971572563789872.png" src="projects/project-167897/images/6468971572563789872.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The legend and the upper left is what you get by default, the one in
upper right is what you get with Fn1, middle right with Fn2, and
bottom right with Fn3. Middle left is what you get when you hold down
the key instead of just tapping it, and upper center is what you get
with Fn1 and Shift.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will need to actually modify this a bit, to add right Alt key —
because that is how you do Polish accented characters on the Polish
keyboard. But I think I can just do it as holding down the Alt key.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still need to learn this layout — I’m not normally a touch typist,
more like a hybrid one, so this requires some getting used to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-167897/log-170457/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2019-11-01 in project-167897.</summary>
    <published>2019-11-01T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>
