<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>http://deshipu.art/</id>
  <title>deshipu.art - Posts in project-25256</title>
  <updated>2024-08-07T20:37:31.480161+00:00</updated>
  <link href="http://deshipu.art/"/>
  <link href="http://deshipu.art/blog/category/project-25256/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://ablog.readthedocs.org/" version="0.10.33">ABlog</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-25256/log-62543/</id>
    <title>Power</title>
    <updated>2017-07-04T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="power"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2017-07-04 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-25256/#project-25256"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Ye Olde Nowt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ZeroLiPO module doesn’t work very well with this power-hungry
display. Adding a big capacitor across the power helped somewhat, but
you can still see problems when the display has a lot of white to
show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now I’m just powering the whole thing from a 1S LiPO battery
directly, without any boost converter or other circuit. That works
well, due to reasons described in &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://hackaday.io/project/9461-lifepo4weredpi/log/32161-3v-or-5v-thats-the-question"&gt;this project log&lt;/a&gt; , and I’m actually quite happy with this. However, there is no
overdischarge protection, and I need to manually switch the power off
after the raspberry pi shuts down – there should be a better way to do
it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I started looking around for a ready module for that – what can I
say, I’m lazy – and was quite surprised that I couldn’t find anything
like that. OK, fine, I will just have to build my own. I looked around
a bit for similar projects to steal from, and found this one: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.mosaic-industries.com/embedded-systems/microcontroller-projects/raspberry-pi/on-off-power-controller"&gt;http://www.mosaic-industries.com/embedded-systems/microcontroller-
projects/raspberry-pi/on-off-power-controller&lt;/a&gt;  – it’s a very nice schematic, and it only uses one GPIO pin to both
signal the pi to shutdown, and see when it finished. I might still
make this, because it’s generally useful, but for now I have a better
idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That project log I linked, it’s for a project that exactly fits my
needs. &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.tindie.com/products/xorbit/lifepo4weredpi/"&gt;And that project is available to buy on Tindie.&lt;/a&gt;  It’s a battery, a charger, a touch pad button for switching it on and
off, and I2C for battery monitoring and low power shutdown. It does
everything I need. I will probably try to put a smaller battery in it,
so that it fits the size of the pi zero better, but that’s it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-25256/log-62543/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2017-07-04 in project-25256.</summary>
    <published>2017-07-04T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-25256/log-63232/</id>
    <title>Honey, I Shrunk Our LiFePO4</title>
    <updated>2017-07-17T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="honey-i-shrunk-our-lifepo4"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2017-07-17 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-25256/#project-25256"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Ye Olde Nowt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both the new PCB and the &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-9461&lt;/span&gt;  arrived while I was away, so I can now get back to hacking. But what
is this? It’s too long for the the Raspberry Pi Zero, as it was
originally designed for the Raspberry Pi B, which is a little bit
longer. But fear not, I anticipated that problem and ordered a smaller
LiFePO4 battery, that should be just the right size. Now it’s just a
matter of replacement of the battery basket:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-25256/images/9626621500311268597.jpg" src="projects/project-25256/images/9626621500311268597.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess I will need to cut that PCB a little bit too. Oh well. I also
removed the female headers from the power module, in order to solder
it flat on top of the hat. Unfortunately, there is one pesky SMD
resistor getting in the way there, so it won’t be completely flat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other news, I’m really happy with the through-hole buttons, they
are much easier to solder and fit in that tight space – although I
didn’t find color ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still need to get a display for this – either order another one, or
desolder one from the first prototype.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-25256/log-63232/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2017-07-17 in project-25256.</summary>
    <published>2017-07-17T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-25256/log-63366/</id>
    <title>Power Button</title>
    <updated>2017-07-19T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="power-button"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2017-07-19 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-25256/#project-25256"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Ye Olde Nowt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Independently from hacking the LiFePO4 power module, I decided to try
and make a small module with a soft power button on it — the same I
linked two logs ago. I will use a thin PCB, so that it can be inserted
between shields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="https://644db4de3505c40a0444-327723bce298e3ff5813fb42baeefbaa.ssl.cf1.rackcdn.com/d454a77d40b39efe53f67d91cc78e32c.png" src="https://644db4de3505c40a0444-327723bce298e3ff5813fb42baeefbaa.ssl.cf1.rackcdn.com/d454a77d40b39efe53f67d91cc78e32c.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The schematic is based on several designs from various forums — I’m
not smart enough to figure it out myself. Pressing the button switches
the power on and latches it. Subsequent pressing of the button does
noting, except pulling the GPIO4 down to let the Raspberry Pi know
that we want to shut down. A long press (or pulling the GPIO4 low)
forces it off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-25256/images/4635311500417505751.png" src="projects/project-25256/images/4635311500417505751.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a little bit more complex than I’m comfortable with, but we will
see how well it works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-25256/log-63366/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2017-07-19 in project-25256.</summary>
    <published>2017-07-19T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-25256/log-64434/</id>
    <title>Version 2.0</title>
    <updated>2017-07-31T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="version-2-0"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2017-07-31 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-25256/#project-25256"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Ye Olde Nowt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second version of the PCB arrived some time ago already, but I was
struggling with the ways to power the raspberry pi and didn’t really
try them. Now I confirmed that the new layout of the buttons works
perfectly fine with just the device tree overlay. I didn’t test the
memory for storing that overlay yet — there will be a separate update
log for that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I assembled all three of the PCBs I got from OSHPark this time, and
with the second display I used a low-profile female header, instead of
soldering the module’s pins directly into the board — so now I can
unplug the display. I also experimented with two kinds of switches:
the standard through-hole clicky switches, and a weird SMD switch with
very soft and springy action. I’m not yet entirely sure which ones I
like better, to be honest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-25256/images/1769581501512137788.jpg" src="projects/project-25256/images/1769581501512137788.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, and I still didn’t try the audio amplifier either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Either way, the PCBs work, they mostly use through-hole components for
the basic functionality (minus the sound and the memory), and you can
order them from OSHPark here:  &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://oshpark.com/projects/TfXEKJ7T"&gt;https://oshpark.com/projects/TfXEKJ7T&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-25256/log-64434/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2017-07-31 in project-25256.</summary>
    <published>2017-07-31T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-25256/log-64912/</id>
    <title>Power Button Fail</title>
    <updated>2017-08-09T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="power-button-fail"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2017-08-09 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-25256/#project-25256"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Ye Olde Nowt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PCB for the power button arrived some time ago, and recently the
last of the parts made it into my mailbox — the pair of mosfets in a
single package. So I went and assembled everything, and powered it up,
and what do you know, it didn’t release blue smoke. But it also didn’t
work — it was always on. So I went through the schematic again, and
then asked on the hack chat channel for help. Rubber-ducking helped
and I noticed that I have swapped the P and N mosfets in my design.
Ugh. I also tried the PCB on the zero, and turns out it doesn’t fit
quite right — the HDMI socket is a little bigger than I thought and
needs a deeper cut out. So here’s a new version of the PCB:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-25256/images/5858491502295919000.png" src="projects/project-25256/images/5858491502295919000.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully that one will work better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-25256/log-64912/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2017-08-09 in project-25256.</summary>
    <published>2017-08-09T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>
