<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>http://deshipu.art/</id>
  <title>deshipu.art - Posts in project-18758</title>
  <updated>2024-08-07T20:37:31.230417+00:00</updated>
  <link href="http://deshipu.art/"/>
  <link href="http://deshipu.art/blog/category/project-18758/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://ablog.readthedocs.org/" version="0.10.33">ABlog</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-18758/log-49883/</id>
    <title>Just Starting</title>
    <updated>2016-12-04T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="just-starting"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2016-12-04 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-18758/#project-18758"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Mechatronic Ears on the Micro:bit&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was thinking what could kids make with the micro:bit, I
remembered my &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-9769/#project-9769"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Mechatronic Ears&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  project. The micro:bit has a built-in accelerometer, can easily
control up to three servos (because that’s how many pins are easy to
access without an edge connector), and can be programmed in Python. So
I decided to give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started by collecting the materials: a hat, ears with hair clips
(you can find them in any costume shop, or order from China), two
9-gram servos (the cheap SG90 would work just fine, but I didn’t have
any at hand, so I used some random beaten up servos left from my first
robot experiments), a battery, some wires and a piece of steel wire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-18758/images/189921480804987540.jpg" src="projects/project-18758/images/189921480804987540.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;hr class="docutils" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started by opening the ears – just cutting the thread on the pink
inside. Be careful to only cut the thread and not the material – we
will need to sew it back together at the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-18758/images/9381541480805058008.jpg" src="projects/project-18758/images/9381541480805058008.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, I put the servo arms on the servos, and cut them to only have an
arm on one side (I lost the original one-sided arms for them, you can
use those for your servos, of course).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-18758/images/1208811480805179354.jpg" src="projects/project-18758/images/1208811480805179354.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, I bent the steel wire, and put it through the holes in the servo
arm:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-18758/images/7722661480805220561.jpg" src="projects/project-18758/images/7722661480805220561.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I bent both ends again (using pliers), so that it sits tight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-18758/images/94781480805278457.jpg" src="projects/project-18758/images/94781480805278457.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I cut the wire to the length of the ears.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-18758/images/6838121480805316041.jpg" src="projects/project-18758/images/6838121480805316041.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I bent the wire into an arc, so that it can go along the edge of
the ear (the wire is bent at the tip, so that it doesn’t poke out).
Then I put the servo with the wire inside the ear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-18758/images/9229531480805366998.jpg" src="projects/project-18758/images/9229531480805366998.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I initially wanted to sew both the serwo and the wire in place, but in
the end decided to simply glue the servo to the bottom of the ear
(where the hair clip is) with instant glue. Be careful to not get fur
glued to your fingers. Then I fastened the steel wire to the edge of
the ear, but only from the tip to about halfway towards the servo –
the rest has to stay loose, so that the servo can easily move.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-18758/images/1310961480805556383.jpg" src="projects/project-18758/images/1310961480805556383.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, I connected wires to the micro:bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-18758/images/4080741480805681892.jpg" src="projects/project-18758/images/4080741480805681892.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yellow goes to the pins, red goes to 3V, and brown goes to GND. One of
the servos had its original wires broken, so I had to replace them
with some randomly colored ones… Look at the other one for
reference.Next, a quick test using the servo code from &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-8643/#project-8643"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Micro:Bob&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe style="width: 500px; height: 281px;" width="500" height="281" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="None" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/aSmmwRwKM5Y"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see the servo “buzzing” when it’s outside of its allowed
range. I experimented a bit to find the optimal range for this
particular ear, when it’s not buzzing – it was 120-180. Bending the
wire a bit helped with the range. The second ear had range 0-90.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, when everything was read, I sewed the ears up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-18758/images/1947031480806062300.jpg" src="projects/project-18758/images/1947031480806062300.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second ear was made exactly the same way, except you have to
remember to make it a mirror image of the first one – so everything
has to be reversed.Once I had both ears, I attached them to the hat. In my case, I just
used the hair clips, since the hat had holes in the right places
already. You might need to sew them, or to make the holes for the
clips, or to attach them in some other way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The micro:bit and the battery go inside – I will need to secure them
there somehow, I will probably just use black thread.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-18758/images/4701661480806206012.jpg" src="projects/project-18758/images/4701661480806206012.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s it for now. Next up, programming them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-18758/log-49883/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2016-12-04 in project-18758.</summary>
    <published>2016-12-04T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>
