<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>http://deshipu.art/</id>
  <title>deshipu.art - Posts in project-174121</title>
  <updated>2024-08-07T20:35:28.743908+00:00</updated>
  <link href="http://deshipu.art/"/>
  <link href="http://deshipu.art/blog/category/project-174121/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://ablog.readthedocs.org/" version="0.10.33">ABlog</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-174121/log-181706/</id>
    <title>PCB</title>
    <updated>2020-08-02T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="pcb"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2020-08-02 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-174121/#project-174121"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Handheld Wing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was ordering PCBs anyways, so I slapped this together quickly. I was
in a hurry, so you will have to excuse me the right angle traces and
somewhat shoddy looks. Since it would be a waste to order a PCB and
not do something new with it, I’m experimenting with SMD pin headers
for the first time here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-174121/images/9094201596393683927.png" src="projects/project-174121/images/9094201596393683927.png" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-174121/images/4292801596393691356.png" src="projects/project-174121/images/4292801596393691356.png" /&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-174121/log-181706/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2020-08-02 in project-174121.</summary>
    <published>2020-08-02T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-174121/log-182223/</id>
    <title>Assembled</title>
    <updated>2020-08-14T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="assembled"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2020-08-14 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-174121/#project-174121"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Handheld Wing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PCBs arrived a while ago, but I was still waiting for the SMD pin
headers. Those arrived today, so I assembled it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-174121/images/2723121597439376372.jpg" src="projects/project-174121/images/2723121597439376372.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using those headers for the first time, I’m actually quite happy with
them. The only problem I can see is that the default Fritzing
footprint for them makes the pads really large, so there is a lot of
wiggle room to how they can be soldered — but you need quite precise
positioning for the headers to work with the feather. Soldering
manually is not a problem, because you simply plug a feather into the
headers to make sure the spacing is right. But if I were to have this
assembled in a fab, it would be a problem — possibly using a footprint
with smaller pads would solve that problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also assembled the case from some left-over laser-cut pieces I had
from the previous prototypes. The d-pad and button caps needed some
improvising, I just glued them from several layers. It’s not pretty,
but it’s good enough for prototyping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-174121/images/4467901597439687891.jpg" src="projects/project-174121/images/4467901597439687891.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I can try and port my games to various exotic feathers. But of
course that involves coding, and that requires much more motivation
than I have, so it will be probably be a while.\&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-174121/log-182223/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2020-08-14 in project-174121.</summary>
    <published>2020-08-14T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-174121/log-203934/</id>
    <title>RP2040</title>
    <updated>2022-03-11T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="rp2040"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2022-03-11 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-174121/#project-174121"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Handheld Wing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn’t really do much with this project for a year, but recently I
wanted to order some more &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-165032/#project-165032"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;PewPew M4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; boards for a workshop, and realized that with the current chip
shortage, the SAMD51 chips I used are impossible to get. So I think I
need to now make a version of PewPew M4 with the RP2040 chip on board.
I already had one attempt at it, doing research for  &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-178061/#project-178061"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;PewPew S2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; , but what I need now is not a bigger and better device, but exactly
the same as PewPew M4, but with a chip that you can buy. So I dug out
this project to try it with the RP2040 Feather, and see if there are
any traps lurking for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, there don’t seem to be any. I added the missing resistors,
plugged in the feather, wrote a ugame.py for it, and it just works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-174121/images/6820061647028627828.jpg" src="projects/project-174121/images/6820061647028627828.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the next step will be to design a PCB similar to that of
PewPew M4, but with the RP2040 chip on it, and that is going to be
some more work. You see, the SAMD51 only needed two capacitors and a
resistor. The RP2040 needs that, plus a flash chip, a crystal
oscillator with its own capacitors, and possibly more. So now I need
to figure out what is needed exactly, and design the PCB for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, I could simply use a Pi PIco, but that would mean I
have to give up on he expansion header.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-174121/log-203934/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2022-03-11 in project-174121.</summary>
    <published>2022-03-11T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>
