<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>http://deshipu.art/</id>
  <title>deshipu.art - Posts in project-159733</title>
  <updated>2024-08-07T20:45:03.482940+00:00</updated>
  <link href="http://deshipu.art/"/>
  <link href="http://deshipu.art/blog/category/project-159733/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://ablog.readthedocs.org/" version="0.10.33">ABlog</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-159733/log-166847/</id>
    <title>New Source</title>
    <updated>2019-08-09T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="new-source"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2019-08-09 in &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-159733&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://makerfabs.com/pewpew-standalone.html"&gt;You can now buy PewPew Standalone directly from Makerfabs&lt;/a&gt; , instead of Tindie. What does it mean for you? Well, for one it is
cheaper, because there are no additional payments and handling along
the way. The shipping is about the same, but you get registered mail
for that price, so it’s actually cheaper too. Oh, and it comes already
fully assembled, and in any color you like, as long as it’s black.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally I am very excited about this, because in practical terms in
means that more people can get their hands on it, and that I’m free to
focus on the support, documentation, more games and the next version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Big thanks to &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://hackaday.io/hacker/268569"&gt;&amp;#64;Makerfabs&lt;/a&gt;  — they helped me with all of my bigger projects, and they have always
been very reliable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-159733/log-166847/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2019-08-09 in project-159733.</summary>
    <published>2019-08-09T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-159733/log-167788/</id>
    <title>Workshops in Zürich</title>
    <updated>2019-08-25T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="workshops-in-zurich"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2019-08-25 in &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-159733&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The weekend of August 31st and September 1st,  &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://hackaday.io/hacker/94159"&gt;&amp;#64;Christian Walther &lt;/a&gt; and me are going to run workshops on game programming with
CircuitPython using the PewPews.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will have a unique opportunity of becoming a full-stack game
developer: starting with assembling and soldering your game console,
through a simple bouncing ball tutorial, to a full-fledged game for a
PewPew, all in just 2-4 hours!\&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-159733/log-167788/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2019-08-25 in project-159733.</summary>
    <published>2019-08-25T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-159733/log-169295/</id>
    <title>Noc Informatyka</title>
    <updated>2019-09-27T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="noc-informatyka"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2019-09-27 in &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-159733&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is another secret project that I can now write about. At the
EuroPython I have been approached by the organizers of a Polish event
Noc Informatyka ( &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://nocinformatyka.pl/"&gt;https://nocinformatyka.pl&lt;/a&gt; ) and asked to prepare badges for the event. I agreed, and we produced
150 custom units.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-159733/images/9690931569586876025.jpg" src="projects/project-159733/images/9690931569586876025.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electrically it’s identical to the PewPew Standalone, including the
voltage regulator that is optional for Standalone, but included by
default here. Mechanically, I used the same large LED matrix as in the
EuroPython PewPews, but this time with a vertical arrangement of the
device and with quiet silicone buttons, same as used in &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-27629&lt;/span&gt; . The connector header has been moved to the bottom, to make room for
the lanyard hanger, and there is a place for writing the participant’s
name. The battery holder for two AAA batteries is on the back, which
is otherwise empty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The units were produced and tested by &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://hackaday.io/hacker/268569"&gt;&amp;#64;Makerfabs&lt;/a&gt; , and it all went very smooth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can’t wait to see what the participants of the event will do with
them!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-159733/log-169295/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2019-09-27 in project-159733.</summary>
    <published>2019-09-27T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-159733/log-173081/</id>
    <title>PicoPew</title>
    <updated>2020-01-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="picopew"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2020-01-18 in &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-159733&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t think I have written about it here yet, but there is one more
member of the PewPew family of devices, and this time it’s not made by
me, which makes me really happy. I’m talking about the a project by &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://hackaday.io/hacker/94159"&gt;&amp;#64;Christian Walther &lt;/a&gt; called &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-167369&lt;/span&gt; . You should go there and read the project logs, I think they are
interesting and very detailed. It’s much more powerful device, with a
bi-color matrix with 256 possible colors, esp32-based with TinyPICO
wifi board as the brains, and a really small form factor. I have
obtained a working one by trading both with Christian and with
Unexpected Maker for a &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-165032&lt;/span&gt;  (one for the shield, one for the TinyPICO).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here it is all assembled, and with an enclosure that Christian
3D-printed for me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-159733/images/6647671579382122629.jpg" src="projects/project-159733/images/6647671579382122629.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still need to get all the software on the device, but so far it
seems to be functioning as expected. I love how the Pew library has
worked here as a kind of a base standard, on top of which more
functionality is built. I didn’t anticipate this, but maybe it will
really become a platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-159733/log-173081/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2020-01-18 in project-159733.</summary>
    <published>2020-01-18T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-159733/log-191485/</id>
    <title>Better Buttons?</title>
    <updated>2021-04-08T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="better-buttons"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2021-04-08 in &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-159733&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buttons are always a huge problem in a hand-held device. Sure, when
making the prototype you can just slap any tact switches on there, and
they work well enough. But for something like a game console, where
you are going to be pressing those buttons a lot of time, the feel
they provide is very important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can dismiss right away most of the metal switches available out
there — their stem is too small to be pressed comfortably multiple
times, and they require quite a bit of force to be pressed as well.
Unless you are also doing custom case and key caps, they are simply
not suitable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The standard 6mm tact switches are not completely hopeless. They are
common and cheap, come with the stems of different heights, and
sometimes you can even find versions of them with lower than regular
actuation force, which helps a lot. But they still are pretty hard and
noisy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then you have the “quiet” silicone switches, which look great, with
their large square stem, but feel extremely mushy. There is
practically no tactile feedback at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But recently I found one more source of buttons, which have very nice
feel. I didn’t see them before, because they are not sold in the “tact
switch” category, and they are usually through-hole, not SMD (though
can be hacked for that). I’m talking about the buttons that are used
in computer mice. They used to be very large, and thus unsuitable for
our small devices, but recently there are versions of them that look
very much like our tact switches, except they have much lower
actuation force and much more pleasant and crisp click. After all,
they are for clicking your mouse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an experiment, I replaced the tact switches on one of my PewPew
prototypes with those switches, and I am very pleased with the
outcome:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-159733/images/6455601617889700312.jpg" src="projects/project-159733/images/6455601617889700312.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see, the stem is rather small, but it’s big enough to be
pressed comfortably. The travel is short, and the actuation force is
small, but the click is very pronounced and satisfying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see on the photo that one of the switches has its legs bent —
this, together with small pieces of the legs visible on the opposite
side, makes it possible to solder it to a reguar 6mm SMD tact switch
footprint. However, there is really no reason for PewPew Standalone to
use only SMD switches — I could easily add holes to the footprint, to
make such buttons an option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also found some “low-profile” versions of mouse button switches,
that are only 4mm high, but they are “quiet”, with the click being
much quieter and less satisfying — but they are still much better than
regular tact switches, due to much lower actuation force and travel.
I’m considering using them in future handheld devices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-159733/log-191485/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2021-04-08 in project-159733.</summary>
    <published>2021-04-08T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>
