<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>http://deshipu.art/</id>
  <title>deshipu.art - Posts in project-188908</title>
  <updated>2024-08-07T20:46:55.838281+00:00</updated>
  <link href="http://deshipu.art/"/>
  <link href="http://deshipu.art/blog/category/project-188908/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://ablog.readthedocs.org/" version="0.10.33">ABlog</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-188908/log-214801/</id>
    <title>The PCB Design</title>
    <updated>2022-12-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="the-pcb-design"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2022-12-30 in &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-188908&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is my first project where I completely switched to EasyEDA as a
PCB design tool. I honestly tried KiCAD several times over the years,
and it’s just so hilariously bad at exploring designs, that I gave up
on it. EasyEDA is still far from ideal (especially the copper fills),
but it’s not completely unusable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, I followed up on my fluffbug work, of course, but I made
everything except for the battery holder surface-mount. I found some
pretty nice low-profile smd female headers on LCSC, and the IDC
connectors for the servos also exist in SMD versions. This actually
gives me much more room on the PCB, because headers no longer take up
both sides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-188908/images/4419021672440629343.png" src="projects/project-188908/images/4419021672440629343.png" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-188908/images/7571221672440647456.png" src="projects/project-188908/images/7571221672440647456.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are still a few pilot holes for all the components, so there was
some work squeezing it all to fit, but in the end it came out rather
compact. Since the headers are double-row, I can use them to add
bigger “face” shields for the robot, with things like displays,
cameras, sensors or speakers. In fact, I went ahead and designed two
shields, one the size of the pico with a camera, and one bigger, with
an oled display and a speaker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-188908/images/630771672440827528.jpg" src="projects/project-188908/images/630771672440827528.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-188908/log-214801/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2022-12-30 in project-188908.</summary>
    <published>2022-12-30T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-188908/log-214803/</id>
    <title>The OLED Face</title>
    <updated>2022-12-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="the-oled-face"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2022-12-31 in &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-188908&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PCBs arrived right after the holidays, and I quickly assembled
one, moved the whole legs from one of my fluffbugs, and here it is,
all working as expected. I just had to update the pin names in my
circuitpython code, that’s literally it. But then I decided to try and
get to work one of the shields – the one with a display and a speaker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-188908/images/9751991672441425672.jpg" src="projects/project-188908/images/9751991672441425672.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The display just worked. I used the SH1106 library for displayio, and
I just had to rotate the display 180° and add a 2-pixel horizontal
shift to adapt it to this particular display. I got really good with
that working on all those handheld game consoles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The speaker turned out to be a bit more challenging. I used a
MAX98357A I2S amplifier, because I had that on a module earlier and I
was confident it works well. Well, despite the schematic being
practically the same with the module (minus some unnecessary caps, as
usual), this one didn’t work. The chip is a bit small QFN package, but
visually it looked soldered well. I tried a lot of different things,
until at fifth re-soldering of the chip with the hot-air gun, it
suddenly started working. I suppose looking good is not enough. Of
course with such a tiny speaker the quality is questionable, but it
does sound properly robotic, and it’s surprisingly loud (I hardwired
the amplifier to maximum gain).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-188908/log-214803/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2022-12-31 in project-188908.</summary>
    <published>2022-12-31T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-188908/log-228292/</id>
    <title>Going Smaller</title>
    <updated>2024-03-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="going-smaller"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2024-03-18 in &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-188908&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Smaller robots are easier. Mostly because of the cube law, which says
that the weight of a thing grows proportionally to the third power of
the size. A robot twice larger is 8 times heavier, and accordingly
needs more power to move, bigger batteries, and more robust materials,
which are in turn harder to shape. On the other hand a robot that is
half the size could be 8 times lighter, needing proportionately less
of everything. So if you are a beginner robot builder, you want to
start small.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But not too small! You want to use off-the shelf components, and to be
able to work with your hands, preferably without a need of a
microscope or special processes. So there is a sweet spot in the size
of the robots. When I started with &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-180025&lt;/span&gt; , that size was mostly dictated by the size of the servos that were
available. The 9g cheap blue hobby servos were basically the cheapest
and easiest to source actuators for a robot that you could get, and
the size of both Fluffbug and Moo Bug that is based on it were mostly
based on the size and strength of those servos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But situation changes, the popularity of super-small remote controlled
models grows, and the sub-micro-servos used in them are becoming
widely available. You can now buy 2g servos for only a little bit more
than the 9g servos, and since they are later design, they actually
have better features. They work with single LiPO voltages, and they
often have larger rotation range. They also use much smaller
connectors, which lets you save space on the PCB.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been exploring the use of those smaller servos with the &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-188909&lt;/span&gt; , and I’m pretty happy with what you can do with them and a small
board like the Xiao. However, sometimes you want to have more pins, so
you can add a display, a speaker, maybe some extra servos for hands,
additional sensors and so on. So I decided I need a Wee Bug with the
pi pico footprint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s how I came up with the version 3.0 of the Moo Bug. You might be
surprised here, if you followed the logs of this project before: I
never mentioned anything about the version 2.0! That’s true, I had
that version designed, the main change was getting rid of the servo
connectors and going back to the standard servo plugs. But I never
made or published it, so it’s lost to history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-188908/images/7562251710800246631.png" src="projects/project-188908/images/7562251710800246631.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Version 3 switches to through-hole pin headers for the pi pico, to
save space, and moves the servo sockets under the microcontroller
board. I used a sideways type of sockets this time, so they are pretty
low profile. Cable management might be simplified, because you can
just tuck the extra cables under the board.\&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The electronics is pretty much the same as with the Xiao: battery
protection, battery charging, and an accelerometer. The switch and the
charging LED have been moved next to the servos, to make room for the
servo sockets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-188908/images/9704591710800373247.jpg" src="projects/project-188908/images/9704591710800373247.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The servos are connected to the pins on the bottom row, so that pi
pico clones with a display or other extra features can be used. The
mobility of the legs is slightly limited by the wider top of the body,
but that doesn’t interfere with walking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with the Wee Bug, the legs are made of PCBs, not laser-cut acrylic
– at this size the cost difference is negligible, especially when you
need to find very thin acrylic sheet. Of course they could also be cut
from MDF or 3D printed, at this weight the material doesn’t make much
difference. I’m even thinking about a papercraft version of the robot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-188908/log-228292/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2024-03-18 in project-188908.</summary>
    <published>2024-03-18T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>
