<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>http://deshipu.art/</id>
  <title>deshipu.art - Posts in project-27257</title>
  <updated>2024-08-07T20:35:29.929670+00:00</updated>
  <link href="http://deshipu.art/"/>
  <link href="http://deshipu.art/blog/category/project-27257/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://ablog.readthedocs.org/" version="0.10.33">ABlog</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-27257/log-67341/</id>
    <title>Rotating Everything</title>
    <updated>2017-09-17T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="rotating-everything"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2017-09-17 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-27257/#project-27257"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Fritzing Tricks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rotating elements is easy. You just use the “rotate” button in the
bottom left corner of the screen, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-27257/images/720671505666678552.png" src="projects/project-27257/images/720671505666678552.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, yes, you can do that and that works fine most of the time. But
there are limitations. By default, that button rotates things by 90°.
Some objects can be rotated by 45° by clicking on the small arrow on
that button, and selecting the appropriate option for the pop-up menu.
But some things, such as vias and holes, can’t be rotated at all.
Initially that makes sense. After all, why would you want to rotate a
round hole or via — they look the same no matter how they are rotated!
However, you might still need to rotate a set of holes or vias, or a
mix of parts (like your whole design, for example) that includes holes
and vias in it. And Fritzing won’t let you do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had this problem with an Adafruit Feather shield that I was
designing — it’s slightly longer than 5cm, but my board house would
only make 5×5cm boards cheaply, anything larger costs extra. But I
figured out that I can fit this shield into the 5×5cm outline if only
I rotate it by 45°. But how can I do that when it contains vias and
holes?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking for a way to do this, I found this “rotation” property in the
side pane:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-27257/images/5683771505667163031.png" src="projects/project-27257/images/5683771505667163031.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This lets you rotate a single object by pretty much any angle, not
just multiplies of 45° or 90°. In particular, you can rotate your PCB
by any amount, even though that red button only lets you do 90° for
the PCBs. Neat! But I can’t use that when I have multiple objects
selected, so it doesn’t solve the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wish I could also figure out the next piece of the puzzle myself,
but I actually found it on the Fritzing’s user forum. You see, the PCB
has one property that other objects don’t have — the “sticky”
checkbox, right under that rotation property:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-27257/images/3913921505667409946.png" src="projects/project-27257/images/3913921505667409946.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When an object is sticky, whenever you move it, it will also take with
it all other objects that touch it. And rotation counts as movement
here. So all I had to do is make my PCB sticky and set its rotation,
and everything on it rotated together with it. Presto!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, sometimes you want to just rotate a few selected parts.
Then you can drag a second PCB onto your design, make it sticky, put
all the parts you need rotated on it, rotate it, and then delete the
PCB and move the parts back where you need them. A bit hacky, but
workable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-27257/log-67341/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2017-09-17 in project-27257.</summary>
    <published>2017-09-17T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-27257/log-67389/</id>
    <title>Trace Aesthetics</title>
    <updated>2017-09-18T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="trace-aesthetics"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2017-09-18 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-27257/#project-27257"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Fritzing Tricks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve been putting this post off for some time now, but we need to talk
about this sooner or later. Fritzing became infamous in the
electronics community for the characteristic ugly traces that are
often done with it. People new to the whole thing just connect the
holes and pads in straight lines, adding a bend sometimes when
necessary, and call it a day. It looks something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-27257/images/4729141505729345377.png" src="projects/project-27257/images/4729141505729345377.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s wrong with this, you ask? All the connections are there, so it
will work fine, after all, no?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, there is a number of things wrong. First of all, you are just
being lazy, and that’s a sure warning sign that most likely there will
be other problems with this design. Second, this is not pleasant to
look at, and more importantly, to work with. It’s not easy to see what
is connected where and to modify this design. It’s also easy to miss
shorts between the traces. Finally, there are actual technical reasons
why this design is sub-optimal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You probably have heard about radio-frequency emissions from traces.
Turns out that every trace is basically a small antenna, and it will
waste energy by emitting radio waves. Most traces are not particularly
good antennas, but the ones that have a lot of sharp angles and are
not surrounded by copper fill are better at emitting noise. Unless you
are working with gigahertz signal, this is not the technical reason
for worrying about sharp angles, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are etching your own boards, you have to be very careful about
all the nooks and crannies in your design. The etchant will tend to
pool int them, and eat out much more copper in those places, leading
to possible faulty boards. This is not the technical reason for
worrying about sharp angles if you send your design to a professional
board house for fabrication, though. Neither is the fact that because
of the lack of a copper fill, a lot of copper has to be etched away
and a lot of the etchant wasted on that, and the etching process will
take a lot of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the sharp corners are more likely to peel off the board,
especially if it’s subject to any mechanical stresses or bad storage.
Again, not much of an issue with professionally made boards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it still looks very bad, and all the people who ate their teeth on
the above-mentioned limitations will shudder at the sight of it. So
please, be a nice person and spend the minimal extra effort to
actually make it look good. Start by aligning all the traces so that
you only have horizontal, vertical and diagonal lines (you can hold
ctrl+shift while moving the trace for Fritzing to help you with it):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-27257/images/6087081505730301267.png" src="projects/project-27257/images/6087081505730301267.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Much better already, don’t you think? Now let’s get rid of those sharp
angles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-27257/images/7798151505730730947.png" src="projects/project-27257/images/7798151505730730947.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s starting to look right, doesn’t it? Note that I actually left a
couple of right angles in there — in the T-junctions, and also for the
traces that are too close together to actually do a nice gradual turn.
Personally I think this is fine, but for the reasons I listed above,
opinions vary. Finally, let’s add a copper fill:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-27257/images/3810631505730903031.png" src="projects/project-27257/images/3810631505730903031.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Et voila! A decent looking PCB design. It wasn’t so difficult after
all, was it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course there is much more to it than just the horizontal and
vertical lines and sharp angles. But this is already a start. If you
keep practicing, looking at other people’s designs, etc. you will come
up with your own set of good habits that make the designs nicer,
easier to read, less likely to contain mistakes, and more pleasant to
work with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-27257/log-67389/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2017-09-18 in project-27257.</summary>
    <published>2017-09-18T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-27257/log-67721/</id>
    <title>Net Labels</title>
    <updated>2017-09-24T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="net-labels"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2017-09-24 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-27257/#project-27257"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Fritzing Tricks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s talk a little bit about schematics. I know that you rarely visit
that tab, but if you want other people to actually make sense of your
project, you have to document it. Like I did with my &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-18120/#project-18120"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;D1 Mini Matrix Shield&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-27257/images/2448341506280430055.png" src="projects/project-27257/images/2448341506280430055.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really tried to make it readable. However, the LED matrix has such
ridiculously random pinout, and there are so many connections, that
it’s really difficult to make sense of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I’m a little bit wiser and I use the net labels, which you can
find in your parts pane under schematic view:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-27257/images/4687771506280554982.png" src="projects/project-27257/images/4687771506280554982.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way you use it, you connect it in place of a wire, and at the
other end you make another one, with the same name. Fritzing considers
all the labels with the same network name on them connected. The
resulting schematic is much easier to read, like the way I made for &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-21578/#project-21578"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;PewPew FeatherWing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-27257/images/7132411506280998450.png" src="projects/project-27257/images/7132411506280998450.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, this is not a silver bullet. If you overdo it, and all your
connections are just some random labels, your schematic will be even
harder to read. But if you can think of a name for a given connection,
it’s probably a good idea to use a label for it.\&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-27257/log-67721/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2017-09-24 in project-27257.</summary>
    <published>2017-09-24T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-27257/log-148597/</id>
    <title>Custom PCB Outline</title>
    <updated>2018-07-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="custom-pcb-outline"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2018-07-01 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-27257/#project-27257"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Fritzing Tricks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the greatest advantages of Fritzing over other PCB software
currently on the market is its ability to SVG files directly, without
any need of converting or tracing them. Since it uses SVG internally
for anything, it’s only natural that the PCB outline is also an SVG
file. I’m going to tell you here how I go about making custom PCB
outlines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Usually I start by designing everything on a standard rectangular PCB,
keeping in mind the rough shape that I am going to need. Here’s an
improved design for the &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-9769/#project-9769"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Mechatronic Ears&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  with a power switch added:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-27257/images/4296261530465949010.png" src="projects/project-27257/images/4296261530465949010.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, I export the design as an SVG image:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-27257/images/1906711530466066806.png" src="projects/project-27257/images/1906711530466066806.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I open it in Inkscape, where I can easily draw my desired board
outline:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-27257/images/3724381530466194782.png" src="projects/project-27257/images/3724381530466194782.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Usually I pick some nice, partially transparent color (green, blue and
purple work well) and draw the shape of the PCB I want with it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-27257/images/6047871530466476852.png" src="projects/project-27257/images/6047871530466476852.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also add some silkscreen:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-27257/images/490381530466625269.png" src="projects/project-27257/images/490381530466625269.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, I remove all the Fritzing stuff from the image, and leave only
the board outline and the silkscreen:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-27257/images/7048951530466741327.png" src="projects/project-27257/images/7048951530466741327.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now create a new layer in Inkscape using_Layer→Add Layer…_ menu option, and name it “board”. Select the board outline, and then
select_Layer→Move Selection to Layer…_, then select the newly created layer “board”. Repeat that with the
silkscreen, except call it “silkscreen0” for the bottom, or
“silkscreen1” for the top (you can have both).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are almost done. Unfortunately, Inkscape doesn’t call the layers
the way you tell it — it only adds labels to them with your names. We
will need to go a little bit deeper to actually modify the layer IDs.
Open the XML Editor, you should see something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-27257/images/6197001530467275980.png" src="projects/project-27257/images/6197001530467275980.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now you can select each of the layers, select the “id” attribute on
the right side, and enter new value for it on the bottom. Change the
IDs to “board”, “silkscreen0”, “silkscreen1”, etc. so that they match
the labels. Don’t forget to click Set each time, or it won’t get
saved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are done. Now you can save your board as “Plain SVG”, and go back
to Fritzing. In Fritzing, select the PCB, and in the properties click
on the_load image file_ button:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-27257/images/3061981530467466742.png" src="projects/project-27257/images/3061981530467466742.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Select your saved SVG image. You should see a summary telling you how
many cutouts (slots) your PCB has — make sure that number is correct.
Finally, you will need to adjust the position of your PCB to match the
components, and you are done:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-27257/images/4986671530467729063.png" src="projects/project-27257/images/4986671530467729063.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, when you export the board as gerbers, I recommend to do one more
step before you send it to fabrication: open the board outline in a
gerber viewer, such as “gerbv” and verify that the generated shape is
indeed correct. Fritzing has some very annoying bugs around the gerber
generation, and you might be unpleasantly surprised if you skip this
step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="projects/project-27257/images/1155181530467888431.png" src="projects/project-27257/images/1155181530467888431.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time everything is correct. If it wasn’t, I would go back to
Inkscape and add a couple of nodes to the shape, around the places
where something went wrong, to make sure it’s correct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-27257/log-148597/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2018-07-01 in project-27257.</summary>
    <published>2018-07-01T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://deshipu.art/projects/project-27257/log-148636/</id>
    <title>Tented Vias</title>
    <updated>2018-07-02T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="tented-vias"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published on 2018-07-02 in &lt;a class="reference internal" href="../../../projects/project-27257/#project-27257"&gt;&lt;span class="std std-ref"&gt;Fritzing Tricks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This trick was originally described by &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://hackaday.io/hacker/72667"&gt;&amp;#64;Arduino Enigma &lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;span class="xref std std-ref"&gt;project-91895&lt;/span&gt; . Tented vias are vias that are covered with soldermask. If you think
about it for a moment, there is really no reason for a via to be
exposed (unless you re-use it as a test point). Its job is to connect
the layers, and it does it as well when it is covered. On the other
hand, when it’s covered, the risk of shorting it is smaller, and the
board can look much better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately Fritzing doesn’t normally give you the option to have
the vias tented. But there is a simple trick to add the soldermask
over them when you are generating the gerbers. Start by generating
your gerber files as usual, and once you do that, select_Routing→Select All Vias_ from the menu, and press the Del key to delete them. It will also
delete some of the traces, but don’t worry about it. Now generate
another set of gerber files, in a separate directory, and close
Fritzing without saving the file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now all you have to do is to copy the_maskTop, maskBottom, silkTop_ and_silkBottom_ files from the latter directory to the former, and voila, your vias
are now covered with soldermask. You can also only copy only some of
those files to only have the vias covered on one side of the board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://deshipu.art/projects/project-27257/log-148636/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Published on 2018-07-02 in project-27257.</summary>
    <published>2018-07-02T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>
